.
>> good afternoon.
Welcome to the MAY 6th, 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan chan present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor engardio
and engardio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmood mahmood
present supervisor mendelsohn
present mendelsohn present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sardar
sartor present supervisor
cheryl cheryl present
and supervisor walton walton
present MR. PRESIDENT all
members are present.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk the
san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the ramakrishna
colony who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula as the
indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the
ramakrishna loni have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homelands.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
ramakrishna aloni community
and by affirming their
sovereign rights as first
peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible, with liberty
and justice.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv and today
particularly haim ashbury who
were record each of our
meetings and make the
transcripts available to the
public online.
>> MADAM Clerk, do you have any
communications?
Thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes you to
attend this meeting in the
board's legislative chamber
within city hall on the second
floor in room 250.
Or you MAY watch the proceeding
on sfd of tv's channel two six
or view the livestream at ww w
dot S.F. Geo vtv.Org.
You are able to submit public
comment by email.
Just send it to box at S.F.
Gov.Org or address an envelope
to the san francisco board of
supervisors.
The number one DR. Carlton b
goodland place city hall room
244 san francisco, california
941022.
Make a reasonable accommodation
under the americans with
disability act or to request
language assistance.
Please contact the clerk's
office at least two business
days in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to our consent agenda
items one through seven.
>> items one through seven are
on consent.
These items are considered to
be considered to be routine.
>> if a member objects an item
MAY be removed and considered
separately.
>> colleagues, does anyone want
to sever anything from the
consent agenda?
I don't see anyone so MADAM
Clerk please call the roll on
the consent agenda on items one
through seven supervisor
and engardio and engardio I
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor mandolin middleman I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
and supervisor dorsey dorsey I
there are 11 eyes without
objection these ordinances are
finally passed MADAM Clerk
let's go to our regular agenda
new business item number eight
item eight this is an ordinance
to amend the administrative
code to remove the
authorization for certain cash
revolving funds for the
comptroller.
The ethics commission, the
department of police
accountability, the planning
department, the public defender
and for the department of
public health, the community
mental health services vacation
or rehabilitation and the
laguna honda and for the public
utilities commission for the
hetch hetchy project and the
water department.
This ordinance also reduces the
maximum amount of cash
revolving fund for the human
services agency.
The treasurer tax collector
and the zuckerberg san
francisco general hospital.
This ordinance increases the
maximum amount of cash
revolving fund for the public
utilities commission
and authorizes additional
revolving funds for the public
utilities, consumer recreation
and parks department and the
department of elections.
>> colleagues seeing no one on
the roster let's take this item
same house, same call.
>> without objection the
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk please call
items nine and ten together
items nine and ten are two
resolutions that approve
contract amendments for the
department of public health
and with two contractors to
provide mental health
and substance abuse treatment
services to extend the term by
three years from JUNE 30th 2025
for a total term of JULY 1st
2018 through JUNE 30th 2028.
Item nine approves the fourth
amendment to the agreement with
community forward S.F. In $19.7
million the contract increase
for a new amount of 42 million
and item ten approves the
second amendment to health
right 360 that agreement
and authorizes a one 141.4
million for a new total amount
of 305.4 million.
And I think we can take these
items same house, same call
without objection the
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 11.
>> item 11 is a resolution to
retroactively authorize the
department of public health to
accept and expend an in-kind
gift of food supplies and other
in-kind items in the amount of
approximately 284,000 from the
san francisco public health
foundation in support of food
pharmacies at the department of
public health clinics JULY 1st,
2020 third through 2023 through
JUNE 30th 2020 for let's take
this item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call
items 12 and 13 together.
>> items 12 and 13 are two
resolutions that approve a
grant agreement and an
amendment to a separate grant
agreement for the department of
disability and aging services
with home bridge inc for the
provision of contract mode
in-home supportive services for
item 12 this is a four this is
a term of four years from JULY
1st 2025 through JUNE 30th 2029
$39.6 million increase from
JULY 1st 2025 through JUNE 30th
2026 with additional amounts
for subsequent years to be
requested in the spring of 2026
and item 13 this approves the
first amendment to increase the
amount by approximately 2.4
million for a new total amount
of approximately 144.68 million
with no changes to the term of
five years from JULY 1st 2020
through JUNE 30th 2025 we'll
take these items same house,
same call.
>> without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call
items 14 and 15 together items
14 and 15 are two resolutions
that approve and authorize to
grant agreement amendments for
the public utilities commission
.
Item 14 executes the third
amendment to a contract for
engineering services for south
ocean beach coastal erosion
and wastewater infrastructure
protection with moffitt
and nichols ag as joint venture
to increase the contract amount
by 7 million for a new amount
of 12.75 million and to
increase the contractor ation
by six years for a new duration
of approximately 15 years.
SEPTEMBER 26th, 2018 through
SEPTEMBER 25th 2033 to continue
providing engineering design
and support services for the
ocean beach climate change
adaptation project and for item
15 this resolution executes the
first amendment to a contract
for engineering services for
transmission pipelines with
aecom technical services inc to
increase the contract amount by
7 million for a new contract
amount of 14 million with no
change to the contract duration
to provide for additional
engineering design and support
services for the transmission
pipeline capital improvement
project to fund funded by the
water enterprise capital
improvement program we can take
these items same house, same
call without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
MADAM Clerk please call item 16
and 17 together.
>> item 16 and 17 are two
resolutions that approved to
lease agreements for the
airport commission.
>> item 16 approves the
automated teller machine
service be lease with wells
fargo national association for
a three year term with one two
year option to extend the term
exercisable at the sole
and absolute discretion of the
airport commission with a
minimum annual guarantee of
350,000 for the first year of
the lease and for item 17 this
approves the automated teller
machine service lease a with
bank of america national
association for three year term
with one two year option to
extend again at the sole
and absolute discretion of the
airport commission and a
minimum annual guarantee of
250,000 for the first year of
the lease.
>> and we can take these items
same house, same call without
objection these resolutions are
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call item
18.
Item 18.
This is a resolution to
acknowledge requirements for
the 2024 grant application to
the state of california energy
commission charging
infrastructure for government
fleets for an approximate $5
million grant.
Let's take this same house,
same call without objection the
resolutions adopted MADAM Clerk
please call item 19 item 19
this is a resolution to approve
the first amendment between the
office of contract
administration and inter vision
systems llc for the purchase of
networking equipment, software
and hardware software support
manufactured by juniper
networks inc to increase the
contract amount by
approximately 34 million for a
total amount of 74 million with
no change to the contract term
through JANUARY 31st 2027
and again same house, same call
without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call
items 20 through 24 together
items 20 through 24 we'll start
with items 20 through 22 which
are three resolutions that
authorize the mayor, the
mayor's office of housing
and community development to
execute three standard
agreements with the california
department of housing
and community development.
The cd under the affordable
housing and sustainable
communities program.
Item 20 is the standard
agreement for approximately
29.5 million.
It's a total award to include
19.6 million dispersed by the
cd as a loan to the balboa lea
avenue lp for 100% affordable
housing this is a project at 11
frida kahlo also identified as
the balboa reservoir or
building e and 9.9 million to
be dispersed as a grant to the
city for public transportation
improvements near the project
for the duration through
NOVEMBER 30th 2042 and to
authorize the mayor cd to
accept and expend 9.9 million
in a grant for transportation
and streetscape and pedestrian
improvements and other transit
oriented programing
and improvement item 21 this
standard agreement is for a
total award of 45.7 million to
include 33 million disbursed by
cd as a loan to the balboa
gateway lp again for 100%
affordable housing at the frida
kahlo way project and approved
12.7 million to be disbursed as
a grant to the city for public
transportation and improvements
near the project for the
duration through NOVEMBER 30th
2043 and to authorize the cd to
accept and expend the grant of
up to approximately 12.7
million for transportation
streetscapes streetscape
and pedestrian improvements
and other transit oriented
programing and improvements.
And item 22 the standard
agreement under the infill
infrastructure grant program is
for an approximate $20 million
award dispersed by cd is a
grant to the city for
infrastructure improvements
related to property located at
the balboa reservoir building e
and reservoir balboa reservoir
building a four 100% affordable
housing projects and for the
period starting on the
execution date of the standard
agreement to JUNE 30th 2030 as
amended and four items 23
and 24 to approve and authorize
the department of homelessness
and support of housing to
execute a joint application
with the following entities to
the department of housing
and urban development for a
homekey plus grant for item 23
authorizing a joint application
with the 835 turk street llc
for the homekey grant to fund
the property located at 835
turk street in a total amount
of approximately 18 million
and for item 24 authorizing a
joint application with the 1035
vets llc for the property
located at 1035 venice avenue
in a total amount of 37.5
million and for both 23 and 24
the maximum award amount
allowed under the no for the
notice of funding availability
whichever is greater.
>> supervisor melgar thank you
PRESIDENT Middlemen.
I just wanted to express my
gratitude at to chair chan
and the members of the budget
committee for scheduling
and approval of items 20
through 22 to the staff at ewg
for being creative and flexible
in making sure that this
project could go forward.
This is 17 acres of asphalt
that will be turned into a new
neighborhood.
The most impactful development
project we've had in district
seven in decades and so I am
really grateful for all the
work that it has taken to get
us this far.
We're going to be breaking
ground this year and again
thank you to my colleagues
and thank you to the mayor's
office for pushing this
forward.
>> thank you.
And let's take these items.
Same house, same call without
objection, these resolutions
are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 25.
>> item 25 was referred without
recommendation from the budget
and appropriations committee.
This is an ordinance to
appropriate approximately 5.4
million from the general
reserve and 311,000 of boarding
of prisoners revenue and to do
appropriate 86.3 million from
salaries mandatory fringe
benefits vehicles, programmatic
projects, capital renewal
projects and building
and structure improvement
projects and appropriate
appropriate approximately 61
million to overtime in the
police department and 30
sheriff's department to support
the department's projected
increases in overtime
and approximately 1 million to
building and structure
improvement projects
and building repair in the
sheriff's department supervisor
walton thank you so much
PRESIDENT And MADAM
And colleagues.
>> as you know we held a
hearing on police overtime
in last week's budget
and appropriations committee
meeting last wednesday.
I had a couple of follow up
questions for the department of
human resources that I did not
get a chance to ask and so I
wanted to bring up artist gram
from the H.R.
And thank you so much for for
being here this afternoon but
my question is because I
believe that it was represented
by chief lazaro at last
wednesday's hearing that they
received permission from d h r
or support from the H.R.
Not to enforce the ten b
overtime section of the mou.
>> is that true?
i'm not aware of that.
Supervisor so do we know who
MAY be aware of it in the
department?
>> I can certainly ask in the
department and get back to you
but I'm not aware of it and we
can we come back to this item
because I asked you to ask for
a director eyes and somebody
who I knew would be able to
answer the question does anyone
object to coming back to this?
Okay, so we will we will see if
we can the answer to supervisor
walden's question and we will
come back to item 25 later.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Uh, MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 26?
Item 26.
This is an ordinance to amend
the planning code and the
zoning map to establish the
alexander rhea theater special
use district at the northwest
corner of geary boulevard
and 18th avenue to allow a
density bonus and modification
to existing zoning controls for
a residential project in the
special use district subject to
specified conditions and to
affirm the second determination
and to make the appropriate
findings.
>> supervisor chin thank you
PRESIDENT Mandolin colleagues
this project really has been a
long time coming for the
richmond and there was many
different version and vision
for this space.
So first I want to thank the
planning staff tina tam
and shannon ferguson for their
work on this item.
I want to thank san francisco
heritage for their partnership
in guiding us through this
process and of course I also
want to thank the community
that has been so patient for us
to as we continue to move this
project forward to where we're
at today.
And thank you chair marshall ga
and the land use committee for
sending this item to full board
with recommended asian
colleagues.
This project shows that when
our community demands respect
and love for our neighborhood
we can work together to bring
forward a project that delivers
for the community.
And I'm pleased that the
developer of alexandra theater
,MR. York lee and his team
responded and is ready to move
forward with respect this you
know for our community as well
and they're delivering much
needed family housing for the
richmond this project now also
in the form of the special use
district before you today as a
legislation will allow up to
eight stories structure seven
575 units of 2 to 3 bedrooms
have housing with 12% on site
affordable housing and ground
floor commercial space for this
project doe will also show us
the way that we can build
housing while preserving our
history.
You will see that the facade of
alexandra theater will remain
too with the play signed
and the marquee interior with
murals and chandelier
and surely a significant piece
of the history for alexandra
theater.
So I cannot wait to welcome
families moving into this space
and I really hope to have your
support for this project
and this legislation.
>> thank you.
Congratulations supervisor chen
let's take this item.
Same house, same call.
Without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk, can you
please call items 27 and 28
together?
>> item 27 and 28 are two
resolutions initiating landmark
designations under article ten
of the planning code for item
27 this is for the chula abby
early residential historic
district and for item 28 this
is for the alert alley early
residential historic district.
>> let's take these items same
house, same call without
objection these resolutions are
adopted MADAM Clerk, please
call item 29 item 20 nine this
is an ordinance to amend the
administrative code to
establish the long term
remission of substance use
disorders for individuals as
the primary goal of the city's
substance use disorder
treatment policy supervisor
dorsey great.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Mandolin
I colleagues I first want to
express my gratitude to
everyone who engaged on the
recovery first legislation
which despite the brevity of
its one sentence operative
provision became something of a
flash point in our drug policy
debate.
In the end I think that debate
was truly helpful.
It was enlightening
and important and I think
especially as we continue the
drug policy conversation around
a four pillars framework
meaning prevention treatment
harm reduction and enforcement
I know that supervisor fielder
will be hosting a hearing on
four pillars next week.
This is a strategy that
european cities especially our
sister cities zurich,
switzerland have pursued with
some success.
I think there's this is a
framework for real progress
and I'm looking forward to it.
I'd like to think that the
conversation around recovery
first teed that up well for the
recovery first legislation I am
especially grateful to the san
francisco marin medical society
for proposing language that
would enshrine living a
self-directed and healthy life
free from illicit drug use as
the primary goal of our city's
policy for those with substance
use disorders I know some
disagreement remains on both
sides actually the medical
society for example preferred
the medical term remission
rather than recovery.
To me what matters most in fact
all that matters is that we
have an illicit drug free goal
as our public policy northstar
my gratitude to my co sponsors
PRESIDENT Randleman
and supervisors mahmood cheryl
melgar and engardio and sauder
to the supervisors I have
spoken to about it including
supervisor or fielder
and walton and other supervisor
chan and others.
I want to say thanks as well to
some organizations who express
their support for this san
francisco firefighters local
798 teamsters local 665
laborers local 260 the san
francisco police officers
association foundation for drug
policy solution united players
brothers against drug deaths,
drug free sidewalks and many
others.
There are too many people to
thank from the recovery
community so I won't start
listing those folks.
But there are some medical
professionals who really
deserve gratitude for their
input especially DR. Keith
humphreys.
DR. Stan glantz, DR. John ma,
DR. Anthony digiorgio and DR.
Lawrence weiner perhaps
especially from the medical
society DR. Haven who chairs
the san francisco marin medical
societies advocacy and policy
committee and DR. Jason noll,
the medical society's
PRESIDENT.
In the end this legislation
would accomplish what I hoped
it would to align our civic
aspiration with what any of us
would wish for a loved one
struggling with drug addiction,
a self-directed and healthy
life free from illicit drug
use.
I hope I can earn your support
today.
>> supervisor fielder thanks
PRESIDENT.
I want to thank supervisor
dorsey for all of his work
in bringing forward this much
needed policy conversation
and for engaging me on on some
amendments I would propose.
I also want to thank the social
workers, the street outreach
workers, medical professionals
who advocated for a more
expansive and inclusive
definition of recovery and a
substance use disorder policy
that affirms the dignity
and potential of every single
person struggling with
addiction.
I especially also want to thank
as a friend medical society who
advocated for definitions of
recovery and remission that
align with definitions widely
recognized in the medical
profession and reaffirms the
city's commitment to meeting
the drug crisis with urgency.
>> I also want to reiterate
that as we prioritize
connecting individuals those
who struggle with addiction to
treatment programs, we also
have to continue to affirm that
the prevention and reversal of
fatal drug overdoses remains a
core tenet of our city's work
on addressing this overdose
crisis.
>> we're now on track to reach
our second highest number of
overdose deaths ever.
>> factions of the city want to
present a false choice between
harm reduction and treatment
when both are sorely needed
in this moment.
And I look forward to
continuing working with
supervisor dorsey as as one of
the co-sponsors to the hearing
on the four pillars model.
The moment demands all of us to
come together to achieve a
steep and lasting decline
in overdose deaths and the long
term remission of substance use
disorders in san francisco.
So I will be voting in support
of this ordinance.
>> thank you.
Supervisor.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll and item 29 supervisor
and engardio and engardio I
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman hi man
adelman I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
and supervisor dorsey dorsey I
there are 11 eyes without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk please call item 30.
>> item 30 this is a resolution
to determine that the person to
person premise to premise
transfer of a type 48 on sale
general beer, wine
and distilled spirits liquor
license two far east cafe inc
doing business as far east cafe
social club located at 627
greenwich avenue will serve the
public convenience of the city
and to request that the
california department of
alcoholic beverage control
impose conditions on the
issuance of the license.
We can take this same house
same call without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
31.
>> item 31 this is a motion to
reappoint andrea marmo crawford
to the citizens general
obligation bond oversight
committee term expiring
NOVEMBER 21st 2026 we can take
this same house same call
without objection the motion is
approved MADAM Clerk please
call item 32.
>> item 32 this is a motion to
appoint charles lavery
residency requirement waived
for an indefinite term to the
transbay joint powers
authority.
>> we can take this same house
same call without objection the
motion is approved.
And MADAM Clerk, please call
item 33.
Item 33 this is a motion to
approve the mayor's nomination
for the reappointment of mike
chen to the municipal
transportation agency board of
directors term ending MARCH
first, 2029 and we can take
this item same house, same call
without objection the motion is
approved and in 10s we can go
to our 230 special order I
think maybe these special order
at 2:30 P.M. Today is the
recognition of commendations
for merit maria's service to
the city and county of san
francisco.
>> there we go.
Very well done MADAM Clerk
and we will start today with
district two supervisor cheryl
thank you PRESIDENT Mandolin
and colleague fgs today I'm
here to commend kopechne coffee
if you would please join me up
here.
I'm really excited to see you
so could be a good coffee.
Very proud as part of our
celebration of 2025 small
business week and asiana
american and pacific islander
heritage month here in the city
and county of san francisco
located at 1443 lombard street
in our marina district, capco
is san francisco's first
indonesian coffee shop bringing
the warmth, hospitality
and flavors of indonesia to the
heart of our city.
>> co pico was co-founded by
adi yousuf, amanda schnitzer,
ben ng and vanessa graciela who
have built a space that goes
beyond coffee.
It's really a community hub
rooted in culture, tradition
and connection and with the
support of city programs
through the office of small
business, capco is able to open
its doors in 2023 they received
assistance with permitting
participated in the first year
free program and secured
funding for accessibility
improvements.
Bing echo coffee is their other
business venture that supplies
the coffee that also I make at
home in the mornings too where
their other co-founder brian
thea nadeau is currently
in indonesia finding the right
coffee beans but from your
pandan lattes to nestor which
is my personal favorite it
which is pineapple shortbread
everything on their menu brings
their dedication to quality
and craft right to the fore.
But beyond their product, what
makes copycats stand out to me
is your commitment to the small
scale sourcing from indonesian
farmers your values of
sustainability
and representation.
I'm so grateful to you three
the capco team is chosen the
marina is home from their their
small business.
You've really added something
meaningful to the neighborhood
and to our entire small
business community in honoring
kopi.
>> q today we celebrate not
only their entrepreneurial
spirit but also the rich
cultural contributions of the
indonesian and broader small
business and aapi community
here in san francisco.
Adi amanda ben congratulations
and again and I'd like you to
invite you to the podium where
you already are to say a few
words.
>> thank you.
Thank you so much.
I haven't seen all of you at my
coffee shop so yeah.
>> okay.
Twice so now that someday
hopefully I can open in another
district sorry nothing personal
but it's too close if it's on a
feel free to open a second
location in ours.
>> that's great.
So please come and check us
out.
We are so humble and thank you
for giving us this opportunity
but try indonesian coffee is
great.
>> I know there's a 32% looming
but hey this business can only
to me only happen in some
cisco.
That's why I love this city
and we get all the support that
so far that we need from the
city.
>> so thank you.
Thank you so much.
Dynasty is from yeah my my mom
actually personally made the
the pineapple shortbread so
with her expertise in baking we
wanted to keep pushing like
indonesian snacks and goodies
to san francisco community
thank you.
Thank you yeah yeah.
Next up district three
supervisor sorter all right.
I would like to please ask lily
low and clive lee of bee
chinatown myron lee, laura lee
of culture printing
and jonathan seat of chinatown
volunteer coalition to come up
here to the podium.
>> it is my honor to recognize
these individuals today
and celebrate one of
asian-american and pacific
islander heritage month
and small business week.
>> I want to specifically honor
a beloved chinatown leader lily
low or as the community calls
her auntie lily her
organization be a chinatown
provides bilingual services to
small businesses in chinatown.
Whenever a small business has a
need or a concern auntie lily
is there and she also runs a
little thing you might have
heard of it's the chinatown
night market and it was just
named the best night market
in the entire country by usa
today day and we did it and I
know that many of us have
visited this monthly chinatown
night market and we've seen the
best of san francisco
and chinatown on display at
that night market.
But what some of us MAY not
have seen is everything that
happens before and after that
night market and that is where
all of the hard work is put
in and hours and hours the
night before these night
markets this entire team is out
there setting up into the wee
hours the morning after this
team is out there breaking down
the tables, breaking down the
tents whenever I go I can't
even talk to anti lily because
she's running around.
She's helping carry boxes,
carry trash out whatever
whatever needs to get taken
care of and really takes care
of it and you know, it's really
a coalition of community
members that make this possible
and it's a recipe a recipe for
a very successful chinatown
night market which has included
chinatown is favorite promoter
myron lee included print
and marketing expertise from
laura lee of culture light
printing and really I think
importantly and critically the
involvement the support of the
younger generation and of the
volunteers and that's led by
jonathan of the chinatown
volunteer coalition.
So I am very excited that
you're all here today.
It is perfect timing coming off
of that honor and also perfect
timing as we celebrate the
return of this momentous event
this friday night in chinatown
friday, MAY 9th.
I expect to see you all there
and I want to appreciate all of
your work on this event and all
your services all year round.
>> and with that and to lily, I
want to ask if you might share
a few words but hold up because
supervisor chen would like to
add to the accolades think tank
is supervisor danny I, I
definitely want to say thank
you.
I got to know auntie lily
during covid why everyone is so
scared of going out
and supporting the neighborhood
supporting a small business.
>> auntie lily is up in the
morning stay until you know
disguise start up and down
walking and making sure our
chinatown our chinatown
communities gets what they need
and our merchants continue to
get the support they need.
you're brave.
You are visionary.
>> you are very dedicated.
I I appreciate you.
I appreciate your leadership
and I appreciate your also
continue the uplifting my
younger generation
and supporting chinatown.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you supervisor sara of
course it all thank you for you
know all of us who have been
here and I'm very humbled to
accept this award of course
this award is not only for
myself so this award is good
for for all of aapi community
and at this time I also would
like to take the time to thank
all the wall and here they are
my backbone and it's coalition
and if this is my family
members become my family.
>> so without them I don't
think it's going to be possible
.
>> of course you know the lori
talent how would you know they
are retired.
They really support it and we
got to continue to work hard,
especially chinatown especially
asian community who are behind
with technology data, one who
need a lot of assistance of
course these are of you know,
my volunteers who work who have
a full time job who are willing
to spend a lot of time, you
know, hand on with you know a
lot of to small business thank
you.
>> so I'm going to turn around
to anyone I.
Thanks all the way.
Yeah just really proud and to
be part of this you know title
nine market has grown so much
from one block to now five
blocks to seven blocks now
earning the number one spot
in the whole country on usa
today.
I'm just really proud that you
know us we're doing this as a
volunteer basis with limited
resources and it's just great
to see like the fruits of our
effort being recognized
especially the fact you know
like the rotary brings
in senior members.
I bring in a new younger
generation of asian american
adults and this is great to see
that we're all able to work
together to make this happen.
So I'm looking forward to
seeing you all on friday right
.
Research is a key.
>> and last but not least from
district eight come on up,
terry aston bennett colleagues
today I am so pleased to be
able to present a special
commendation to terry aston
bennett native san franciscan
fifth generation castro
business owner, lifelong
neighborhood champion and as of
last month twice retired
PRESIDENT Of the castro
merchants terry's great
grandfather hilario de baca
founded cliffs in 1936.
Back then the store sold
magazines, cigars, sewing
supplies, greeting cards
and candy.
>> today clif stocks power
drills, lego toys, kitchen
supplies, home goods, wigs
and glitter to be sure cliffs
is there to meet everyday
neighborhood needs.
Their unofficial motto is if we
don't have it, you don't need
it, terry says the community
takes care of us.
We take care of the community
and we carry what the community
needs.
>> when covid forced everyone
indoors, the store responded
with stay at home decorations,
cookware and puzzles to
brighten the cooped up lives of
customers.
>> but cliffs is also quite
self-consciously a delightful
mirror of the quirky sparkly,
fabulous character of america's
preeminent neighborhood.
The castro would simply not be
the castro without cliffs
though terry was born into the
cliffs clan it was not
inevitable that she would
someday run it.
In 1998 her parents weighed a
lucrative offer for the
building from a pharmacy chain
and thought seriously about
closing terry, who was thinking
about getting a teaching
credential considered it long
and hard and made her choice.
She wanted to keep cliffs open
and agreed to be the next gen
manager.
>> she got more involved in the
community and was elected
PRESIDENT Of the castro
merchants association in 2017
and in 2023 when the
organization again found itself
in need of new leadership, she
stepped up reluctantly to lead
it through the last two years.
She recently passed the torch
on to a new PRESIDENT After
another successful
and productive term.
The castro and its businesses
have had more than their fair
share of challenges through
covid and the post covid era.
but terry has provided steady
leadership through difficult
times.
I am grateful for her wise
counsel her B.S. Free approach
and her abundant kindness
post-presidency.
>> she will I know remain
active in the merchants and the
castro the now maybe with a bit
more time for her family
and extracurriculars like
serving as a volunteer roadie
on the aids life cycle to
support the san francisco aids
foundation.
Terry we love you to pieces
and the floor is yours.
>> thank you so much.
>> I mean, as I've told you all
before, I don't do this for
accolades.
>> they do it because I love my
community and we all have
choices to make and when we see
our community suffering we can
stand up and we can help them
or we can watch it crumble
and I refuse to watch our
community crumble ever.
I love this city.
I love my community and I feel
like my community loves me
in return and the relationship
that we have with the
supervisors office and the
mayor's office and all of you
makes it possible for us to do
a really hard job and I don't
know what the future holds
because in reality I couldn't
wish retail on my children
right now.
But I hope that you know, I'm
going to live to be like 150
anyway so.
But thank you all so much
.
>> all right.
So I believe that we MAY be
ready to get back to item 20
5dh r supervisor walton thank
you.
>> PRESIDENT Amendment and I'll
just repeat the question
and thank you for being here,
MR. Graham.
I believe it was represented at
last week's hearing by chief
lazer that they received
permission or support from d h
r not to enforce the ten b
overtime section of the mou.
>> is that true?
>> during the covid emergency
pandemic emergency we met with
the department and we cobra
wasn't in the last fiscal year.
>> I just want to make sure we
know that yeah I'm not
referring to the lot what
happened in the last fiscal
year we met with the department
and we tried to not limit any
tools in their toolbox in order
to do what they needed to do
and that included the language
around the ten b but that was
during the covid emergency.
>> we have not been in the last
fiscal year so it was not
in regards to the last fiscal
year not that that not that we
have any record up.
No.
Thank you so much.
So police department took it
upon himself to suspend those
provisions.
>> I can't speak to that.
I think that's a question for
the chief to respond to.
>> thank you so much, chief
lazaro, on that question.
>> good afternoon, PRESIDENT
Menem and members of the board
of supervisors.
Supervisor walter, would you
mind repeating your question
please?
>> so it was represented at
last wednesday's meeting that
the H.R.
Gave the police department
permission to not enforce ten b
overtime section of the mou we
just heard from d h r that they
gave you latitude during the
pandemic.
Obviously we were not in the
pandemic the last fiscal year
so my question was then the
police department just took it
upon themselves to suspend the
provisions of the mou.
>> really what happened is we
just never went back to the way
that we had it once we once we
talked with d h r in the fall
of 2021 we had a pandemic.
We had officers who were sick,
retail theft was through the
roof was really high and so as
a result we talked with them
and they gave us permission to
suspend the rule having to do
with calling in sick twice over
a three month period and we
stayed with it all the way to
this day for the reasons that I
spoke about last week trying to
keep crime down, retail theft,
crime down, having officers
available and things like that.
So it just never went back.
>> so because of the reasons
you gave you feel it's okay to
be able to operate in any
manner that you feel?
>> no, that's not correct.
And that misstates everything
that I'm saying right now.
>> I don't think it misstates
because I just heard you say
that you decided 2021
conversations were also
applicable to conversations for
the last fiscal year.
I don't want to get into debate
but I just wanted to make sure
i got clarity on what actually
happened.
Was it d h r or was it the
police department that allowed
that to happen and I think I
got that clarity.
>> thank you.
And we stayed with it.
Yes.
Thank you.
>> and artists I do have
another question.
I'm sorry does the admin code
cap every city employee at 520
hours?
Yes and then I know the
department has the ability to
raise the cap if it's a reason
to demonstrate that you don't
have enough people to perform
duties.
>> and did you raise that cap
to 20 hours for a police
department per individual?
That is not my understanding.
My understanding is that it was
raised to 1000 hours a
thousand?
Are you aware if we have
officers getting more than 1000
hours that is my understanding
,yes.
>> and if so, why would you
raise the cap to a thousand
and we know only 12% of
officers are getting the
overtime.
>> why would we raise it to
1000?
Well, we know only 12% of
officers are receiving overtime
like there's 98% I mean I'm
sorry 88% of the department not
receiving overtime.
>> we get the requests from the
various departments to extend
their cap based on reasons such
as in this case short staffing
,etc. It's up to the
department to determine how
overtime is allocated and for
the members of the department
to volunteer for overtime etc..
Thank you.
Supervisor one supervisor
fielder yeah.
Thank you roger walter for
these questions and thank you
for calling for the hearing on
the audit.
You know the committee audit
and the meeting last week was
pretty illuminating for me.
You know, we heard about
potential abuses of the ten b
program in which private
entities can hire as pd
officers and we've heard
continuously about our staffing
crisis as a pd when
constituents are asking us
where officers are in their
neighborhoods and yet officers
who should have been ineligible
to work the ten b program ended
up working 51,000 hours for
private entities.
So I don't I don't know what to
say to constituents when as a
pd is constantly referring to
the staffing shortage.
>> and for me that's a question
of where is the accountability
and I asked in the committee
meeting last week where is the
accountability for abiding by
and enforcing the mou
and hearing from the city
attorney that the posse can
bring complaints and this is
negotiated between the supposed
upon d h r that leads me to
believe that it's this body
that is responsible for holding
as a pd accountable for being
efficient, effective
and transparent in how
resources are allocated.
And I was I think nothing
exemplifies this concern more
for me than officers calling
out sick on the same day not
all of them but some of them
calling out sick on the same
day that they would then work
ten b in the evening and so I
think as with pd as long
overdue for accountability
and stronger checks
and balances especially on
overtime and that's why I'll be
voting no.
>> supervisor ten o I public
safety is one of the top high
priority that I heard from my
constituents in district 11
and I want to make sure that
our police department is
deploying our resources into
local communities and to
respond to the needs of our
local merchants to help deter
crimes and respond to threats
to our public safety.
>> but unfortunately what we
are seeing is exactly the
opposite here a department that
is enable a systematic pattern
of officers offering their
services as a private security
for hire often I think in in
the downtown area as the
expenses of showing up for our
local communities I know that
this is not what san
franciscans sign up for when
our pa supervisors approve that
the budget for that department
and in this tough budget
deficit years we are facing we
are facing down unprecedented
budget cuts to critical
frontline services.
>> I am very sick to my stomach
of being put in this position
today for to pat in the
department for not having
manage their paper more
effectively and I have serious
concern about the mismanagement
and oversights of our law
enforcement over time about
spending the performance audit
of police department over time
last year demonstrated that the
department failed to manage the
use of sick time inflating our
overtime costs.
This was a mismanagement of
funds and it was dishonest
accountability account this
honest accounting by the
department and it did not go
towards serving our public
interests and our all our
public safety and it is role
public trust between the
department and the public as
sfpd has put us in a very
terrible position especially
considering the massive deficit
that we are facing today.
>> but the money is already
spent these hours already work
and we have to pay for it and I
don't want to support this
appropriation but it feels like
we are being put in a position
to decide whether or not we are
going to pay for our workers
for the hours that they already
pay for.
>> they already work for and I
don't want to see this money is
taking from other essential
direct services that we are at
risk of losing.
>> so I strongly urge that
department to immediately
prioritizing getting things
in order and doing it first
doing your fair share to help
us close our budget deficit not
to inflate a problem in a way
that compromises our ability to
deliver on public safety in our
neighborhoods.
>> and I will and I will be
looking into how we can
legislate around this to
prevent it from happening
in the future.
>> I believe that the
department needs our direction
from the board and this is the
best interests of our cities on
its public safety issues.
>> thank you.
Supervisor mahmood colleagues I
wanted to thank you all for
hosting the hearing last week
on the bsa report and for
hosting this platform for a
larger discussion of the police
and sheriff over time item
and budget appropriations I
think fundamentally what we're
seeing is that we have city
departments like sfpd
and sheriff which do not build
in enough funding for overtime
and structurally run over
budget.
>> my understanding is that
over the past year or two the
departments have implemented
recommendations to improve
those overtime costs.
However, functionally we are
not seeing sustainable
operations.
I understand this issue will
not be solved overnight but the
board and residents alike would
like to see operations improve.
>> public safety is a priority
for the communities of district
five but we shouldn't build
safe neighborhoods on the backs
of burning out our officers
and sheriff's deputies are
spending on overtime with
hundreds of unfilled positions
on the books from what I see.
>> my inclination would be to
not support these continued
practices as I'm sure many of
my colleagues feel.
>> however, in our discussions
with the respective departments
with this legislation failing
would mean is failure would
require the comptroller to
freeze the police budget.
It would prevent non-salary
projects from moving forward
and prohibit pd bills from
being paid.
My understanding is that the
controller would then need to
step in to develop a plan to
stop additional police spending
to pay for what's already been
spent on overtime and the
entrance of maintaining our
public safety operations
and keeping residents safe as a
result.
I will vote yes on a
continuation of public safety
services for our city.
I do feel, however strongly
that we need to see significant
improvement in operations
and recruiting and support
supervisor chan's efforts on
our chan's efforts on figuring
out legislative mechanisms to
ensure we don't encounter the
same situation next year.
I do want to see further policy
changes from these departments
for measurable improvements
with a focus on recruitment
efforts to meet staffing
threshold necessary to reduce
overtime expenses in the coming
fiscal years.
I'm looking forward to seeing
proposals from the lapd on how
they look to fundamentally
solve this problem through
recruiting so that we don't
have to be asking for overtime
increases every year because
for the improved safety of
residents and fiscal
stewardship I would like to see
recruitment line items to
demonstrate intent to progress
this from this current
situation.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor mahmood I think I
might have dropped supervisor
sartor accidentally from the
queue so I think you MAY unless
you took yourself off I think
you're ahead of supervisor
dorsey.
>> thank you.
I will I will take over.
>> colleagues I think clearly
we are faced with lousy options
here today.
On the one hand we face a
choice which would send our
police budget into a fiscal
mess and essentially freeze the
budget.
On the other hand, it is clear
that the department's practices
themselves have been messy
and I hope I speak for for all
of us when I say that wanting
public safety and supporting
public safety should not come
at the expense of basic
transparency, good bookkeeping
and public trust.
>> going forward I expect more
from everyone involved in this.
I would like to see overtime
practices be clarified.
Funds to be used on more
sustainable uses like hiring
and recruitment and most
importantly adding safeguards
to minimize the chances of
abuse in programs like this
and in our committees and in
our legislation I expect that
we will all look to add those
guardrails in the future so
that this does not happen
again.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey thank you
president mandolin.
I will be supporting this item
today but I have as I have said
whenever a public safety
overtime appropriation comes
before me I support this
because the alternative is
unthinkable.
I'm not proud of this vote.
I don't think a well-run city
should ever be in a situation
that requires this much
overtime from our public safety
agencies and one while I will
agree that there should be more
accountability for us of pd
and its management and use of
overtime.
I also think we as city
policymakers need to be
accountable to prioritize
getting to a fully staffed
police department and also to
achieve full staffing in our
sheriff's office and among 911
dispatchers.
In my view this is a problem
in public safety staffing that
we cannot afford to not solve.
There are many public safety
challenges that we face today
that we didn't see coming.
Fentanyl covid 19 there are
things that we had no idea we
would be facing but we have
known for the better part of 30
years that a short staffing
crisis was coming, that it was
on the horizon and that there
was a disproportionately large
generational cohort of police
officers hired in the 90s who
were approaching retirement
age.
And now here we are as we were
going off a retirement cliff
and we are facing a real crisis
in public safety staffing
in police department in the
police department right now.
we are at 75% staffing.
So I will support this item but
I will also support and urge
everybody to support efforts to
get to a fully staffed police
department and to full staffing
in all of our public safety
agencies.
>> thanks.
>> supervisor walton thank you
so much.
PRESIDENT Of management.
I do have a question for the
comptroller because I just want
some clarity to make sure that
officers who already worked
overtime this has nothing to do
with them and no effect on
them.
Correct?
Greg wagner, our city
comptroller is the third
PRESIDENT Of the PRESIDENT To
supervisor.
Walton that's correct.
For hours that have all already
been worked.
Payment has been made via
payroll.
>> thank you.
I just I just want to say I
will never have change with
this department if we don't
stop giving them a blank check.
>> I've been through.
This is my seventh budget
process.
Seventh year having the same
appropriation come to this
body.
They weren't able to forecast
in year one.
in year two.
They weren't able to forecast
in year three.
in year four.
They weren't able to forecast
in year five.
they weren't able to forecast
in year six.
And now we're in year seven.
>> all of our city departments,
all of our nonprofits we tell
them that they need to give us
a budget.
Present it and stick to it.
And we try to hold everybody
accountable.
But this department and I think
is an equitable I think it
demonstrates the fact that some
people have opportunities that
others don't.
And if we do not at some point
reject and force this
department to stay within their
means like every other
department, this will continue
to be the case.
Whether the department is fully
staffed or not because we've
heard that certain rules don't
apply to them under their own
interpretations.
So unfortunately I can not
support this.
Officers that did work overtime
will be paid or have been paid
but this behavior will not
change for this department if
we continue to give them a
blank check year after year
after year.
>> supervise jen.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Mando
min.
I think and probably I do need
the comptroller greg ratner's
help a little bit to kind of
help us walk us through the the
total of the dollar amount that
we're seeing here actually
closer to $100 million
and around $86 million is
really for the police
department and the remaining is
really for the sheriff's
department and out of which
what is really concerning is
really the general fund reserve
dipping into the 5.7 million.
So in a technical sense and I
think that the comptroller
partner can actually help me or
maybe the department can
actually help me.
What we're looking at here
though is that we are within
the department a police
department is shifting their
spending and asking for that
within their existing budget
for this fiscal year
and there's shifting that
spending which is what we call
a salary saving within the
department and we're shifting
that into overtime spending,
correct?
>> police department yeah.
Good afternoon supervisors.
Catherine maguire yes.
Supervisor that is correct.
It is a surplus transfer but
because of the requirements
and amend code we are required
to come for this supplemental
appropriation and somebody
maybe is is the comptroller or
somebody explain the difference
between general farmer's serve
and within the existing
departmental budget and we're
shifting to spending to pay
salary.
Greg wagner comptroller again
that essentially is the
difference where on the place
department side there are
appropriated funds appropriated
a permanent salaries that are
being shifted to a different
use over time and you're
required under the admin code
to bring that shift to the
board of supervisors.
So on the general fund side
and in the sheriff's department
that same thing is also
happening but the total amount
of overtime requested exceeds
the the budgeted appropriation.
And on that side there's a
request in this legislation to
draw funds from the general
fund reserve to be able to meet
the projected spending.
So that is the 5.739 million
that would come from the
general fund reserve and that
would need to be replenished
under our adopted financial
policies in the upcoming
budgetary period.
>> and if we do not approve
this shift of $86 million
and and also for the sheriff
what will happen to and while
you have answered that you know
the officers been paid what
what will happen to the police
department if we do not if they
do not receive this $86 million
.
>> so a couple of things.
We are late in the fiscal year
and a lot of the overtime
expenditures have been
accumulated to the extent that
we have the tools and the
department has the budget the
comptroller's office office
would do things like go in and
restrict spending on things
like capital projects, other
expenditures that are not based
on legal commitments.
So we would do what we can to
control expenditures at this
point in the year.
Realistically we would not be
able to restrict spending
enough to offset the
accumulated and projected over
time right with the remaining
fiscal year to go you will not
be able to offset $86 million
correct?
>> colleagues, it is difficult
choices that we have in front
of us and I'm so appreciative
everybody like having this
conversation because today is
not a county like today's
conversation is really
projecting of what the
conversation to come in JUNE.
The decision that we all have
to make collectively offers of
course, you know for the budget
appropriation committee
and then to the full board if
we're really holding on to this
conversation that we have today
and commit to this conversation
about accountability to our
police department, it is about
time for us to have that
conversation through the budget
process that it is clear to us
if there are wasteful spending
and spending that are like not
accounted for at the same time
we have to make that decision
to figure out like which senior
program that we actually MAY
end up have to cut what youth
services that we MAY have to
see reduction and then most
importantly for security
and not to mention the
challenges that we face
collectively against the trump
administration potentially with
more federal cuts.
And it is a question that I
really appreciate and you have
no idea that you know with this
conversation that four on
display today that there seems
to be a commitment to whole not
just the police department
accountable but I certainly
hope that also the two
departments accountable for
budget overtime spending but as
well as any type of spending
come before us.
you know, I think I am
preaching to the choir here
that, you know, early on
in this year that I have
mentioned choices are only
going to get tougher and that
at one point that when we think
about certain contracts that we
want to approve some programs
that were in the fund but at
the same time we want to
prioritize public safety
and clean and safe streets.
These choices are coming
and are coming really quickly
and I and thanks to board
PRESIDENT And really working
closely with the mayor and
really having those tough
conversation like right now
along with our labor partners
and and I certainly hope that
the police department as you
have heard from my colleagues
today that you know, I think it
is time for us to all step up
to the plate and to figure out
how to reduce wasteful spending
while eliminate wasteful
spending and to make it more
cost effective.
Colleagues, I think it's a very
tough choice and I, I am not
here to sway you to vote one
way or another because I do
respect your choices today.
>> however, while that is being
said, I will be voting
in support of this legislation
or this overtime allocation
simply because the really the
financial reality is that the
city the police department will
not be able to offsets this $86
million of spending.
>> one two is that as we have
talked about is that the very
different from the 2023 when
they come to this body for a
$25 million of police overtime
that was all on the general
fund reserve which means that
they were over spent by $25
million of their budget today
that they're shifting their
salary savings because of
learned lessons from that time
that they're they are shifting
the salary savings to the
overtime spending.
That does not mean that we can
continue to to allow this part
is ongoing without bringing
in the spending in the upcoming
fiscal years because we know
that the got to be some limits
to the spending.
>> and then also I just want to
flag to for the sheriff's
department that they in this
fiscal year actually overspent
by $5.7 million and I to expect
the sheriff's department in the
upcoming fiscal year to show us
the math and accountability
measures and protocols that
they will be putting in place
so that they're not going to
dip into the the midyear
general fund reserve
and spending outside of their
budget.
Not only do I expect them to
spend within their budget but
again also to really have a
holistic conversations and plan
about their staffing and with
that I, I understand and I
respect your choices today
colleagues and but I will be
voting in support.
>> supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Appreciate as I can
go out I just have some
questions for city attorney are
there any limits on you know,
reporting regularly to the
board of supervisors and on
overtime use or projection is.
>> good afternoon supervisors
deputy city attorney brad
rusty, I mean are you asking
whether there are reporting
requirements already or whether
the board could put in place
reporting requirements on this?
>> so I guess both are these
subject to mou provisions?
>> the administrative code
requires the board the
department to come to the board
for re appropriation in these
circumstances like it's
happening now.
So that's part of the the code
already I'm not aware of there
being any other reporting
requirements but I'm not aware
of all reporting requirements
but it is something that you
could potentially impose or ask
them to do.
>> controller thank you
and kate greg wagner controller
there is a requirement for
in our quarterly financial
reports we we do report on
actual and projected over time
so those are at the six
and nine month reports and we
do inform all report at the
three month mark although we
don't usually do a full three
month report.
So we we report on that basis
and we attempt to alert the
mayor's office and the board of
supervisors to any projected
spending above budgeted over
time as early as we identify
it.
>> understood.
Thank you so much.
Supervisor jan thank you
PRESIDENT Random and I do want
to highlight this so colleagues
there's a difference between
the the policy approving
overtime versus the money being
spent while there could be a
report on how much overtime
it's being spent and how it's
being addressed that does not
report on whether that there's
accountability on the actual
overtime.
So I run it also express my
appreciation on the budget
and legislative analyst report
to actually dive deeper beyond
of just the number of dollars
that is being spent and and
sources of funding is really a
different conversation about
policy and operations and that
there's a different whole
different conversation about
holding a city department
accountable about how they
actually spend the money.
While you MAY have the money to
spend on the overtime that does
not necessarily means you
should and I think that is
really the conversation here
today is how and whether they
actually should spend all those
money on overtime.
>> and so I just wanted to say
just because we have a
quarterly report that does not
mean we we shouldn't be asking
for more information.
>> I.
All right, MADAM Clerk, please
call the roll in this item
and item 25 supervisor engardio
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder no supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
I mendelson eyes supervisor
melgar melgar I supervisor
sauder sorter I supervisor
cheryl cheryl eyes supervisor
walton welton no supervisor
chen chin I supervisor chin
chin I and supervisor dorsey
dorsey I there are nine eyes
and two nose with supervisors
fielder and walton voting no
this ordinance is passed on
first reading MADAM Clerk let's
go to the first of our 3 P.M.
Special orders items 34 through
37 comprise the special order
at 3 P.M..
This is a hearing of persons
interested in or objecting to
the decision of public works
dated MARCH 27th 2025 to
approve a tentative parcel map
for a two lots subdivision
and for new condominium unit
project at two through four
addison street.
Item 35 is the motion that
approves the decision of public
works and approves the
tentative parcel map for the
project and makes the
appropriate findings.
And item 36 is the motion to
conditionally disapprove the
decision and disapprove the the
tentative parcel map subject to
the adoption of written
findings and item 37 is the
motion to direct the
preparation of findings to
disprove disapprove the
tentative parcel map.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk so
colleagues, we have before us a
hearing on the appeal of the
tentative map for a project
that 2 to 4 addison street.
The appellant has withdrawn her
appeal although the matter is
therefore no longer before us
out of an abundance of caution
we're still going to act on the
motions and I'm going to
suggest that we approve item 35
and table items 36 and 37.
But before we do that we should
take public comments and if
there are any members of the
public who want to provide
public comment on the
understanding of the appeal has
been withdrawn.
We are we they should do that.
>> MADAM Clerk good afternoon.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Management
and thank you members of the
board of supervisors.
My name is nicole miller and I
am the appellant that I
and I've withdrawn and the
appeal this is because the
developer kindly has measured
back markers and we have a
better understanding of the
boundary adjacent to our
property.
>> but I do want to take this
opportunity to express the
challenge that these types of
developments bring.
>> since the state of
california has enacted the
important measures to improve
and increase housing across the
state, we have swung to another
extreme where now the community
really doesn't have adequate
communication opportunities
and open forums and so we're
left now with individual
neighbors need to call the
planning department needed to
talk to our supervisors one on
one and I would just ask the
board to consider this as we
have more of these developments
the challenges that it MAY
bring.
>> and then lastly I'm going to
take a moment of your time to
bring up something that I'll
bring up with the planning
department.
>> our neighbors have commented
on the traffic in this area
and if I MAY pass you these
handouts or if it's easier I
can show them here we'll we'll
come pick it up from here
and you're welcome to show it
as well.
>> okay, great.
>> so the property is shown
in the the field it's bare
right here.
>> this property has been
undeveloped, you know, since
san francisco has been in place
and my home is the orange
and purple home on the left
hand side and what you can see
at the corner is a light yellow
house and then you can see a
bus stop.
>> well, that corner it doesn't
have a stop sign on bemis as it
turns up, addison and this
little street is used like the
indianapolis 500.
It's quite it's quite fast that
cars drive.
>> so when cars begin to exit
out of the new developments we
are concerned for the safety of
the pedestrians and I'll just
ask you to look at the second
picture.
>> please finish your thought.
This is the children there's so
many children in this
neighborhood and so we'd like
you to consider that these
neighborhood meetings are
important because they talk
about more than just the
building but the neighborhood
impact of buildings.
Thank you.
Any other members who'd like to
address the board at this time?
>> starchild thank you, MADAM
Clerk.
>> first I had a question which
is why was there no public
comment on the last item
regarding appropriations for
the law enforcement agencies
that happens in committee
please proceed.
>> I'll set your timer so
there'll be no time for that
today.
No.
Even though it was heard here
it happened in committee.
>> okay sir.
>> I'll come around and speak
to you.
Let starchild begin his two
minutes.
Good afternoon.
My name is starchild.
I'm chair of the libertarian
party of san francisco.
El paso for.
>> so our website I am in favor
and I believe libertarians are
generally in favor of strong
property rights which means if
you own a piece of property
that should actually mean
something you should be able to
build what you want there
without jumping through a bunch
of hoops.
>> and it used to be like this
that's why 100 years ago even
though san francisco was much
poorer than it is today, there
was not thousands of homeless
people on the streets like
there are today.
We have a homelessness crisis
that continues year after year,
decade after decade for the
last few decades because the
city government and other
levels of government have made
it so difficult and expensive
and time consuming to get new
housing built and things like
this appeal being brought
forward.
Well, I understand
and appreciate concerns these
things should be handled
outside the court of law.
You know, take it to your
neighbors, try to work things
out on a community basis.
don't criminalize people for
using their own property to
build housing.
You know, you can see in the
map that was put up on the
screen a moment ago how much
that is really infill like
there's no reason for that lot
to be vacant.
We need more housing.
It should be allowed to build
housing there.
Please do everything you can to
expedite this and not make
people jump through any more
hoops to get it built.
>> let's get the homeless off
our streets, have more housing
.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comment.
Next speaker please welcome sir
.
Sir, MAY I ask the gentleman
who was in line sir did you
want to speak?
>> okay are you being public
comment this is not general
public comment this is public
comment on items as on items 35
through 34 through 37.
Welcome sir.
Good afternoon.
Board of supervisors is
PRESIDENT Randleman my name is
eric van o'neill.
I am the project sponsor for
the project development at four
addison and this large split
that's in front of you today
and particularly given the fact
that the appellant has
withdrawn her appeal we really
feel that we're following all
the requirements and that this
is a project at least at this
stage which is in front of us
here is a large split which has
been approved tentatively
and we're following all the
correct procedures that are
required and should we be
required to provide anything
that is in the public realm
such as dpw requirements, we're
going to comply with all of
those requirements when the
time comes when we submit
permits and we will also comply
with any other requirements all
the city agencies will require
of us.
>> we trust that you'll oppose
the decision to grant this
tentative approval and we hope
that our neighbor MS. Miller
will be able to have a
conversation with with us
in the proper forums outside of
this realm.
So we're apologetic that we're
wasting everybody's time here
with what seems like a
frivolous situation here.
But we are continue and remain
to be open and are ready
and willing to discuss this
matter as we have been with
MS..
Miller since we discovered this
at the very outset.
>> thank you for your time.
Thank you for your comment or
any other members of the public
like to address the board on 24
through 27.
>> welcome.
Hi, I'm corey friedman.
I live at 36 pima street and I
don't feel like this is
frivolous.
I am appreciative that this
there's a forum here and do you
want to ask because it wasn't
clear as a neighbor what forms
are for conversation especially
if new developers come in to
build condos next door
and there's no neighborly
conversation and if you're not
going to have any more forums
for public comment I would like
to understand what that process
is.
So maybe some of you can help
us understand the new process
processes for that.
I know that's changed recently
so I'll have my staff come
around and take your
information and we'll make sure
the sponsor receives this
information from you.
>> okay?
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comment.
All right, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
A public comment is now closed
and seeing and well seeing that
no other names are on the
roster.
>> item 34 has now been heard
and is filed.
I do want to thank MS..
Miller for for withdrawing for
withdrawing this appeal.
I think that the issues that
she has raised are real and I
hope that the project sponsor
and she will be able to
negotiate with them in good
faith probably a subject
division appeal was going to be
a hard way to get those issues
addressed.
But I wish I wish her well
and hope that everyone is able
to work that out.
If someone in district eight
has questions about development
projects and wants to know what
your rights are, feel free to
get in touch with my office.
MADAM And staff at us of ford
or and we'll try to answer
questions for you.
It looks like the clerk's t
team is also out there to do
that.
MAY I have a motion to approve
item number 35 and table items
36 and 37 moved by melgar
seconded by walton.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll on the motion to approve
item 35 and table 36 and 37
supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I supervisor fielder
fielder eyes supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
I randleman I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sutter
souder I supervisor cheryl
sherrell I supervisor walton
walton I supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chen chin I
and supervisor dorsey dorsey
either are lebanese without
objection item number 35 is
approved and items 36 and 37
are tabled.
>> MADAM Clerk let's go to our
next 3 P.M. Special order item
38.
>> item 38 this is a hearing of
the board of supervisors
convening a committee of the
whole today MAY 6th for the
members to hear and receive
updates on the progress
and implementation status of
the united states department of
justice recommendations
pertaining to reforms within
the police department.
Supervisor walton thank you so
much PRESIDENT MADAM in.
>> colleagues, as you know
there have been many concerns
that needed to be addressed
between law enforcement and the
community.
The 272 department of justice
recommendations for the san
francisco police department
have led to some changes
and improvements for the
department.
but obviously we still have
some work to do to gain that
trust and develop that better
relationship between
communities of color and law
enforcement.
Today's hearing is an update on
where the department is
in regard to those 272
recommendations.
>> and so I would just say
thank you to chief scott for
being here and I believe the
show resource.
>> chief scott thank you
PRESIDENT Mandarin and thank
you supervisors.
Walton I'm going to open it up
with just a brief summary of
the recommendation process.
I know some of the board
members weren't here when we
started this process but I'll
open it up with a brief summary
of where we've been and where
we are and then.
Executive director mcguire will
be here as well to talk about
our plans for sustainable
building and to complete the
remaining recommendations which
are only nine recommendations
out of the 272 that need to be
finalized and completed.
So our city stands today as one
of the only major cities in the
nation to have both
successfully completed a
federally outlined
collaborative reform initiative
and simultaneously reduce crime
across all major categories
according to the final report
that was published this JANUARY
this past JANUARY of this year.
The department's reform efforts
were achieve and I quote this
without any compromise to
public safety, end quote.
And in fact coincided with
again quote notable reductions
in crime throughout the city.
We were found to be
in substantial compliance.
And I just want to give a brief
summary of what that actually
means and highlight the four
key accomplishments that
occurred during this.
Substantial compliance finding
by the california department of
justice.
First of all, our achievement
of compliance with the 272
recommendations was 96.7%
and that equates to 263 of the
272.
This was a major milestone for
our department, particularly
given what led up to that
culvert and everything that
resulted from the aftermath of
the george floyd murder
in minneapolis that really kind
of could have set us back.
But we kept pushing in, kept
focus on the implementation
and completion of those
recommendations.
Reductions and use of force was
a major milestone
and reductions in officer
involved shootings also between
between 2017 and 2023 overall
uses of force incidents
declined across all racial
groups with the steepest drop
involving use of force
declining against people in the
category demographic of black
or african-american.
The average number of officer
involved shootings dropped by
nearly 50% when compared to
2018 to 2023 and compared that
to the prior period of 2011
through 2017.
The next major milestone was
sustained leadership and our
unprecedented commitment.
we dedicated five commanders
full time to shepherd the
reform effort in an
extraordinary commitment of
executive leadership that no
other major law enforcement
agency in the country has
undertaken.
And lastly, as I mentioned,
crime reduction alongside the
alongside these efforts to make
the department better while
implementing one of the
nation's most ambitious police
reform efforts.
At that time our police
department has also reduce
crime rates across all major
categories and we are really
pleased with our ability to
balance improvements and reform
with results that really speak
to our commitment to making our
city a safer city and our
department a better department.
It took a lot of resilience as
they said it took a lot of
commitments.
These were impressive in at
times in policing particularly
after 2020 through 2023
and things really in terms of
our staffing and many other
issues in the department.
We're at a crisis level but we
did maintain our commitment
and complete our obligation to
complete our reform initiative.
So with that there are nine
remaining recommendations, all
of which are tied to a full
launch of our performance
appraisal and management
dashboard slated for a
department wide rollout
in early 2026.
And you'll have a slide here
that you've already seen or
that you'll see in a minute
that outlines what those nine
recommendations are.
And in order in regard to those
particular recommendations, the
aim is to harness and improve
recommendations related to
supervision, accountability,
professional policing
and really hone in and take
advantage of technology to
better our data collection
and our uses of data to make
our department more efficient
and more accountable.
This is how we plan to continue
to sustain reform.
And with the other 263
recommendations that we were
found in substantial compliance
,we actually have a plan to
sustain and make sure that we
don't slide backwards on those
other 263 recommendations.
So that is the overview and I'm
going to ask director mcguire
to come up and definitely open
it up to additional comments
and questions from the board.
Thank.
>> not sure.
There we go.
Hi.
Good afternoon supervisors
and catherine mcguire.
I'm the executive director of
the strategic management bureau
who has been the coordinating
bureau in the department for
the implementation of reform
efforts and reporting with our
collaborative reform partners.
>> as you can see the nine
recommend well in the
presentations admitted and on
the screen here there are nine
outstanding recommendations
that have to do with
performance appraisal rules
and a management dashboard to
inform those performance
appraisals.
we are within a few months of
launching our pilot on this
program and will be working
with an internal working group
to really hone and improve as
we have launched that pilot
and sort of demo and beta test
for lack of a better term.
>> the the new system.
So we are moving to an
electronic based performance
appraisal system and the
performance dashboard
incorporated with that as well
our management dashboard.
>> and I'm happy to take any
questions that you all might
have about these or other
recommendations as well.
>> thank you, chief and thank
you director mcguire.
Obviously the department has
made some strides
and definitely improved
in several different ways
and so one I just definitely
want to acknowledge that I am
still extremely concerned
around the data in terms of
bias around police stops.
But what are we doing moving
forward to address that?
>> oh it's a multifaceted
approach.
So beginning with the new
policy changes.
I don't know the exact
percentage but a large
percentage of our department
general orders have been
updated to reflect modern
policing 21st century policing.
>> that includes our general
order and traffic staff.
unbiased itself and putting
policies in place to really set
the tone and infrastructure
that we are going to take.
You know the disparities there
very seriously with that also
the management dashboard that
director mcguire just mentioned
when that comes online
and it'll be piloted in the
next couple of months.
It also gives our supervision
and our management the ability
to actually take snapshots of
stops stops conducted by
officers to see if there are
patterns that we need to
address before these things
snowball into what we've seen
in the past with huge
disparities.
We have made some improvements
on the rate of disparities as I
mentioned a while ago when
individuals african-american,
black in terms of that
demographic and that is a I
believe because of our
policies, our use of force
policy finding of firearms have
all been revised in the last,
you know, six, seven years
while with this reform
initiative has happened
and we've seen continued
declines in use of force.
So traffic stops disparities
in this in the stops
themselves, disparities in the
use of force.
Those things we believe will be
addressed at least to the point
where we can identify patterns
and trends and then take action
to address them with the data
systems that are about to come
online.
And I see you've made some
changes.
Officer evaluate asians.
>> how often are officers
evaluated?
They are evaluated by
semiannually semiannually
and we have a system called
performance.
Basically the performance
improvement plan system also.
So the actual evaluation is the
same annually for nine officers
but within that evaluation
period supervisors can
implement performance
improvement to address issues
that were performance needs to
be improved.
And I didn't mention this
earlier but another tool that
we use in terms of the question
last question you asked is our
early intervention system which
is also being revised
and upgraded I think we've
talked about that before the
vendor is almost complete with
that project so that gives us
another tool to look at the
performance of our officers,
look at trends, look at risk
management issues and address
those before they become actual
problems.
>> thank you.
>> supervisor chan thank you
chief and thank you director
maguire for your work.
Just trying to understand a
little bit about you've there's
still an ongoing implicit bias
training that is within the
police department and if so how
how does that training
conducted?
Is it on a rolling basis or
when during the police academy
and then you update
periodically how does that
implicit bias training work
and if it's working both?
Supervisor chan thank you for
the question.
It is there modules in the
basic academy where implicit
bias and modules of training to
bias in general and in our
ongoing advance officer
training which every officer
has to do on a on a regular
basis post peace officer
standards and training requires
24 hours of training to be
ongoing and you have to do that
within a two year period so our
officers go to advance officer
training those same modules or
a lot of those same modules or
interviews in the advance
officer training as well.
So that training is ongoing.
There's also even through post
there's online training that
are that our officers have
available to them but it is a
ongoing it just doesn't stop
when officers graduate the
academy and that's something
that is ever evolving.
We've done some other training
outside of the post mandated
training to address that and we
believe that that is effective
training and it'll get better
as we work with academic
partners which we are like
stanford university and some of
our other research and academic
partners centers for the center
for policing equities and there
a couple more that escape me
right now but they actually
give us policy recommendations
and recommendations for the
different types of trainings
that we can do to keep this
discussion and this this topic
moving forward and evolving.
So it is ongoing with every
member of the department.
>> thank you.
And does implicit bias training
also apply to not just the line
officer but your captain,
sergeant lieutenant as well as
commanders like do everyone
in rotation to say not just our
line officer in need of that
implicit bias training but
everyone periodically also
receive that yes from chief of
police through incoming
recruits and then we also have
online training available a
company called basic.
And basically what that is is
vignettes on different is
interactive where officers can
go online and ongoing training
on implicit bias and different
types of scenarios.
So that is something that we've
been doing since the 2020
and that's available for us as
well.
>> and does it I'm not too sure
exactly how it works.
I mean we have it to like for
for us does it does it have
sort of this pass and fail
results and then you kind of
send end up sending somebody to
additional training and how
does that work?
Like I'm just trying to
understand like I mean I we all
go through training from time
to time and sometimes we just
sort of just checking the box.
But I'm just trying to
understand like what happens if
there's a pass and fail or
and and if it does and what
happens if someone fails the
training outcome of training
in general or implicit bias?
Yeah it's scenario based.
I say vignettes and scenarios
and officers have to basically
identify what they're looking
at.
It's not a test that you know
you fail now you've got to go
to some additional training
basically it's ongoing training
and is reflective you know
whatever the scenario is and if
the officer does the
interactive training, the
actual training tells you can
what it is that it wants you to
know about that particular
scenario.
So if you are able to identify
what they're looking for it'll
let you know that and if you're
not you know it'll guide you to
you need to consider these
things but it's not a bet.
It's not a test.
We don't get results of tests
or anything like that here.
I also mentioned that you're
you're now mandated quarterly
meetings with the department
and police accountability who
are you mandating to meet with
them quarterly like who's who's
what is the topic of discussion
sorry I'm just looking at your
sly page 12 that indicated
accountability and reporting
and you mentioned here it says
that your your mandated
quarterly meetings with the
department of police
accountability.
So I'm just trying to
understand like who's meeting
with the police accountability
and my assumption of course is
separate and apart from when
there's police officer required
disciplinary action and this is
different type of meeting.
So I'm just trying to
understand what those quarterly
meeting look like, who attend
them and what are usually the
results from those quarterly
meetings.
>> so we have a process now
and this is been within the the
collab of reform initiative
that this was created called a
discipline review board is
members of the department of
police accountability usually a
higher ranking member is the
chief of staff usually attends
that meeting or their designee
the commanding officer of our
risk management there is a
there's an assigned police
commissioner there
and basically they take
discipline cases where issues
are identified that could be
policy issues, training issues
and they we sit down with
members of dpa and discuss
those issues and try to come up
with recommendations for
solutions.
Their recommendation could be a
policy change, a general order
change or training and that is
a quarterly quarterly meeting
and it's derived from
discipline cases where those
identify those those issues
that are brought to this
meeting are identified.
>> thank you.
>> supervisor fielder thank
you, PRESIDENT Thank you so
much to you scott for
presenting these.
I also commend you on your work
to make sure that our
department follows the blue
ribbon commission reports
and implements all the all the
reforms.
I was wondering because at the
last budget and appropriations
meeting it also came to light
from assistant chief lazard
that the department was
contemplating shortening
training and I just want to
know if any of the proposed
trainings and in this
particular subject area are
being proposed as being cut.
>> yeah.
No the answer is that the
shortening will shorten the
amount of the basic academy
training but the ongoing plan
is to bring the recruits back
to do that training after they
graduate from the academy.
>> so we've looked around other
departments have done that very
successfully.
Sacramento is one of them
and basically it will get
officers out in the field but
it is not going to eliminate
training.
You just happen later
and oftentimes our academy is I
believe probably one of if not
the longest in the state
and the california peace
officers standards and training
which sets the guidelines for
all police training.
There are minimum and in
actuality I think if you just
did the minimums it's about
four and a half months of
training.
Our academy was over seven
months.
>> so we believe that we can
cut some of the things that we
were doing that are speed
centric and move those two post
academy graduation but the
training will still occur.
So we're still in the process
of of timing of all that but we
do not plan to to lower our
training standards.
>> I'm glad to hear that.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Supervisor jen thank you,
PRESIDENT Thank you, chief
scott I've seen the report that
we talked multiple pages start
we talked about technologies so
can you explain a little bit
how technology can help solve
some of the reform?
>> and also I have heard that
in the budget appropriation
meeting that technology also
holds accountability of you
know, the misuse of pay sick
leave so all the ten b program.
>> so can you explain a little
bit more?
>> yeah, I'll open this up
and executive director mcguire
work the oversees technology
among the other functions she
oversees but just to open it up
at a high level there are
management technologies like
our timekeeping system h r m
s they're pretty antiquated to
be quite frank with you
and when those are upgraded we
believe that we might be able
to better address some of the
issues that were raised in the
last session that you just
raised there also technologies
I just mentioned the the early
intervention system technology
the technology that we have is
probably two decades old.
It's needs to be revised
and we've already begun that
process.
We have contractor almost at
the end of actually overhauling
and and bringing a new system
that the new contractor is
benchmark technologies and is a
better integration of many of
our data systems in our streams
of data.
So the management dashboard
that we're talking about would
be tied into that which will
give us more ability to detect
trends, address potential
training issues even some of
the disparity questions that
supervisor walton mentioned we
believe we'll be better able to
identify that because these
systems will bring everything
together.
Then there's that technology
that are helping in terms of
operations when salient example
of how this can be helpful for
not only policing but just
better justice for the people
that we serve.
We've had a couple of scenarios
where by the use of drones we
were able to quickly determine
that the person in fact that we
had detained was not the person
between the drones and the
video surveillance camera
technology was not in fact the
person that committed the
crime.
And our belief and my belief is
that that resulted
in exonerating that person on
the spot.
So I mean a few examples but
that's really important that we
become more efficient, we're
able to solve crimes quicker
which at the end of the day
that's a cost saving and an
efficiency saving we're closing
more cases, we're solving more
cases and those technologies,
those operational technologies
help in that regard.
So I know that's high level
and I'm sure there's a lot more
that executive director mcguire
can talk about and yes,
supervisors thank you for the
question.
To bring it back to reform a
little bit just because the
and I'm actually going to go
higher level for a second which
is the one of several there was
a series of recommendations
about as having a five year
plan for technology and we do
have that for the management
technology piece, sort of the
management of the department.
and so one you know we two of
the systems that the chief has
mentioned are well underway.
One is just pretty much
awaiting policy.
>> the another is we're about
to launch I mentioned it before
we're about to launch a pilot
on or an early model of that
system and then we are in the
middle of the what would be the
beginning of construction for
it to draw an analogy for our
large arms system, our records
management system which would
replace what we use for case
management and records
management I.E. Incident
reporting and then which is the
enterprise the big enterprise
system in the department
and then beyond that is the h.R
system, the human resources
management system which would
help us have a better clearer
more real time picture of
officer hours worked
and compliance with policies as
we set them in the system.
Oh all right.
Well I want to add my thanks
and commendation for your
continued progress on the
collaborative reform
initiative.
It's been a lot of work over a
long time but I do think our
department is far better for
it.
So thank you and thank you
supervisor walton for keeping
us focused on this
and returning to it in full
board committees of the whole
way I think we can go to public
comment.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
This is the opportunity if you
are here to speak on the law
enforcement practice and the
update and findings and the
recommendations, now's your
opportunity.
Let's hear from our first
speaker.
We are setting the timer for
two minutes.
>> MR. Allman just thank you.
Supervisor ralph hillman,
PRESIDENT Of the board of
supervisors.
I'm glad you're still here.
They tried to work well, I saw
it.
>> I'm glad you're MR.
CHAIRMAN.
Comments to the board as a
whole.
>> yes, sir.
I want the safeway to reopen at
geary, fillmore and webster
and london bridge, maryland
and bridge said tear it down
and put housing and something
else in its place.
I say no, it's a safe way that
I went to.
I have this walker there's
other people with walkers
wheelchairs, canes and crutches
that safeway must open once
again.
I will not take no for an
answer then at turk and hyde
you need to help me, angela
urban what's the last urban
alchemy?
Yeah.
They're going to the mayor's
going to cut them.
I say no, no, no, no.
But I want to thank the women
supervisors first and then I
recognize gentlemen after that
.
See what else?
Oh yes, the parking when the
media maids come, of course
they pay their ticket.
But then they're going to be
told there needs to be either
texting or emailing or both to
let the whole the car the
before they're towed so they
can move their car because that
is out that is sick and I have
neighbors from all the country
their car has been towed twice
.
That is out of the question.
You must fix it so other than
that you're doing a magnificent
job.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Starchild please hold your
applause and just to be clear
this is public comment on the
findings and practices
regarding line findings
and recommendations regarding
law enforcement practices.
>> welcome.
Hello.
So it's very interesting that
this took five years to do was
postponed since 2020.
I don't know what was up with
that.
Glad it finally happened today
.
>> there was a lot of talk
about taking seriously
disparities and updating bias
issues and stuff and putting
policies in place for
oversights for S.F. P.D.
And I'm curious how come there
is not just as equal strong
supports for a strong
independent police oversight
commission?
>> shouldn't sf pd have
supported max when he was
replaced prematurely?
>> there is talk about implicit
implicit bias training.
And from 2020 to sorry 20 2012
jesus there was underreporting
of latino and asian arrests by
S.F. Pd latinos being care or
missed categorized as whites
and asians MS. Categorized as
other.
And then in 2023 that same
headline popped up again where
officers were misrepresenting
race.
>> one officer was caught doing
that but it was highly
suggested other officers were
also involved in that.
So how does your implicit bias
training actually work?
Because from 2012 to 2020 three
it didn't.
>> how are you going to prove
that your implicit bias
training works?
>> or you don't have to do that
.
We also were talking about
detecting trends using drones
to exonerate people or systems
all coming together.
I know y'all are really like
excited about a mass
surveillance state especially
with trump in charge and all
that.
>> but for the rest of us this
is terrifying.
>> like what the what the?
>> oh yeah.
Your drones are going to
exonerate me.
Thank you so much.
Buy some more drones.
No, that's crazy talk.
That's stupid.
>> like what the is going on
here?
Thank you for your comments,
starchild.
Please hold your applause.
>> I could go.
Welcome to the next speaker.
I first of all it's not blame
trump.
I sick of it all.
Well, I didn't come here.
I didn't I didn't come here
prepared.
I was walking by.
I ran into chief bill scott.
I I respect chief bill scott.
What I don't respect is
ignorance.
I I got placed in a 35 minute
chokehold in the city of san
francisco that has yet to be
addressed in 2021.
I then spent three weeks
in custody on malicious
prosecution by a democratic
government that wanted to make
everything about race.
>> so let's let let's if we
really want to fix this problem
from what I've heard the
several speakers talk about
instead of making it about you
know oh they didn't you know, I
don't give a if I'm identified
as black or asian straight gay
I don't give a when I give a
about is getting treated with
respect and honesty and dignity
.
>> I've I'm on probation right
now for breaking a window four
years ago.
I'm glad that you think that
this is funny.
I've got an ankle monitor on my
ankle right now.
I've got people smoking
fentanyl outside my window.
I got called a today and I got
called and I got battered today
by someone that lives in my
building that's a freeloading
drug addict and I'm being
investigated for fraud when
I've been out of custody for
two weeks and I'm living
in poverty and I've lived
in poverty with you know, if
she can say, I think I can say
it with this not having a smirk
on our face thinking that it's
funny that I got put
unconscious and she makes it a
trump issue versus a respect
issue if there's going to be a
community here despite my bad
words, despite being a
homosexual I actually do
believe in GOD and you're
supposed to respect it.
>> the authority that has been
granted over you which I
respect authority what I don't
respect is ignorance or abuse
and I'm not blaming chief bill
scott.
>> who I will blame is paul
miyamoto.
We talk about all these people
that are homeless
and everything else or while
earning a half $1 million
salary this is what we get.
>> thank you for.
I will be back.
And daniel sat sir eight times
concluded I was and I've
actually applied for a position
so your time's concluded.
>> my time's up.
Okay.
I know two minutes.
>> I have 35 minutes.
I am sorry about that.
But thank you for your
comments.
All right.
>> let's hear from our next
speaker please.
I haven't seen that on
mainstream man.
You want to step forward, honey
?
>> ma'am, please step forward.
So a little respect.
>> why don't you do the same
and stop talking to me?
>> all right?
please begin.
Hi.
Good afternoon.
I often don't come here unless
there's something to advocate
for.
And quite frankly, we're
in here because negligence
in the sfpd when it's time to
report situations that are
emergencies, we expect for them
to respond in the proper way.
When they don't do that, that
creates a distrust between our
community but also with the
departments in order to work
effectively and efficiently.
We have to ensure that we have
that trust when it's broken it
means that the system isn't
working.
We have to rethink the way that
we collaborate and run our
systems when they're not
working.
Now we're also talking about
implicit bias.
Those trainings are important.
People get harmed.
Neglect happens.
It's a diverse community out
there but there's also a lot of
diverse divisive issues that go
on in this community that can
cause trouble.
And when they're in systems
that is on display clearly when
you go to get help and you ask
because it's an emergency.
And in this case when the
elderly and pleasant when they
didn't have the ability to get
up and go to a police officer,
there's a problem with that.
They couldn't go.
So I stood there and I tried to
report something that happened.
>> so in this case we have to
ensure that proper systems are
working efficiently.
do not let us fail not this
city because we stand up for
each other in this city.
>> don't fail us.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
All right.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
>> board CHAIRMAN Mao roman
and board members.
My name is richard sd peterson
and I don't have any real
complaints today.
I carry around my ratty old bob
dylan bag which my daughter
said don't call it a merce.
But in any event the times are
changing.
You know you're really don't
need a weatherman to tell which
way the wind is blowing.
>> and san francisco is
becoming conservative if you
don't see it just let outside
of your window when the
mayor and his staff or his
group are leave in their large
black subaru.
I mean whatever that kind of
cars calls.
In any event, the wind is going
to be very cold coming from
washington.
>> and we do need to get
together because we are a
sanctuary city and all of us
who are lawyers need to really
stand up and protect those who
are here and protect the laws
that we have on the books.
I've got 43 seconds.
>> I like this little timer
here.
But in any event, something
that I think you ought to
consider since the mayor's
family the house is houses have
been here for a long time is
maybe consider neil hallinan as
a potential commissioner for
the police department.
His family the hollands have
been in san francisco for as
long as houses.
And they would be a good
balance.
So in any event a lot of us
have to duck and thank you for
your comments.
This is a hearing on the update
from the department of
justice's law enforcement
practices not general public
comment.
>> welcome star child.
Thank you.
Before I begin I would like to
raise a point of order.
When we had earlier on the
agenda commemoration and for
various individuals people
in the gallery were allowed
freely to clap and show
applause for each individual.
>> I believe the same courtesy
and due process should be
extended to being able to I'm
going to serve time for our
child being able to clap for
public commenters that is a
restriction on freedom of
speech that is inappropriate to
tell me or anyone else that we
can't clap or show applause for
someone giving public comment
because there's no opportunity
later to do that on an
individual basis and it was
earlier for the whole dog
and pony show of thanking
people which is really frankly
a waste of the public's time.
You know, as much as I'm sure
those people have done good
things and deserve some
appreciation, you know, to take
the government's time and then
to say oh well you can clap for
this but you can't clap for
people who come forward with
other concerns on the agenda I
think is completely
inappropriate.
>> you can clap for people
earning $150,000 plus a year.
You can clap for people living
at home our child this so
anyway hundred and 20s I wanted
to say as regards to the police
reforms I'm curious whether
there's anything in the
department of justice
recommendation or anything else
the police department is doing
or the board is doing to try to
ensure that individual police
officers are required to carry
personal liability insurance
and that their disciplinary
records and infractions
and everything are made public
so that their premiums will go
up if they misbehave and that
way we can have a
self-correcting way for keeping
bad officers who abuse the
public and abuse their trust
and violate people's rights off
the force because they won't be
able to afford their raised
premiums and stay in their jobs
if it's a requirement for them
to carry liability insurance
and they have to pay for that
individually instead of the
taxpayers being forced to pay
for it which right now the
taxpayers are forced to pay for
it and subsidize, you know, the
officers who are engaged
in inappropriate behavior
and abuse and excessive force
and all these kinds of things.
So I think this is a key reform
that I urge if it's not in the
recommendations that it be
recommended and the police
department told to do this
and if it is in the
recommendations to exercise
oversight and ensure they are
following it.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
>> we'll come to our next
speaker.
>> afternoon.
>> my name is joel schwartz.
This is my first time.
I'll do you mind pulling that
microphone is closed.
>> yes.
Sorry.
Thank you.
My name is joel schwartz.
This is my first time talking
at this location and thank you
for having me.
>> we need a whistle blower
department at the dea office
and the superior court
building.
>> I made a report at both
offices and was turned away.
It's not okay.
>> I don't think this the city
cares about hearing
whistleblower reports.
>> we need to have a talk.
The chair biology is dead.
>> thank you, sir.
Sir, we do have a whistleblower
office in in san francisco.
Would you like that
information?
Okay.
I'll have my staff bring that
to you.
Welcome, chris.
>> good morning, barry.
Supervisors.
I wasn't planning on speaking
about this but it's relevant to
what I've been working with
with the department of defense
and the department of justice.
I'm basically all of these
issues and concerns with the
police department, the budget,
the funding.
I'm is basically a big fish
swallowing up a small fish.
There's all kinds of
surveillance is being used.
One bigger surveillance ex-cop
was up the other one.
So I did submit this to chief
eleazar and to the senior
police officials within the
police department.
I spoke with the comptroller
earlier.
I offered him some information
that should resolve a lot of
this issues and the art of war
.
It's very easy to get two sides
fighting for a third party
who's making money off the
weapons.
Like if I had a weapons company
I get two countries to fight.
And they blame each other.
Why I make all the money.
So that's what's happening
in the san francisco.
You're in the middle of a war.
Everyone's pointing the finger
at san francisco and the
department of defense and the
department of justice is aware
of it.
And I'm I'm trying to get san
francisco approximately $5
billion.
It's a lot of money that would
solve a lot of issues.
Some of that's going to go to
veterans veterans organization
organizations.
But a lot of that could be used
for your seawall.
It could be used for your
police department, the
sheriff's department, etc..
So I gave that to the
comptroller greg wagner to send
in an email.
I urge each and every one of
you in this room to meet
concerning this.
And again it's $5 billion.
It was funded in 2015.
So it's not about trump money
or anything like that.
But it's there there's 120
billion unclaimed funds.
So that should solve most of
the issues at least temporarily
.
You still have to hold people
accountable for the budget.
Situational awareness you just
can't keep doing the same
things over and over.
But a lot of that's being
caused by outside influences
third parties.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> are there any other members
of the public who would like to
address the board on the
department of justice?
>> I was.
Okay.
Welcome, MRS. Brown.
Oh.
About public safety.
You know I've been coming here
concerning that for a long time
and I just remember, you know,
being at the hospital when my
son was murdered and I turned
around and the police officers
were there and they said I they
were getting ready to leave
and I asked them where where
they going aren't you going to
solve my son's case?
>> and the words were we don't
get paid for overtime so why
shouldn't we pay them so that
they can work and solve our
children's cases and to bring
ens investigators back from
retirement to solve our
children's cases.
>> otherwise we're going to
continue to keep going back
and forth with this.
>> I say pay them so they can
do the job to take care of our
children's cases so that I
won't have to hear we're not
getting paid for overtime again
.
So this needs to happen.
I've been coming here for years
yet long the police commission
which I will be at tomorrow to
bringing up these issues of
unsolved homicides in cold
cases.
>> I am so glad that we're
finding a way to pay tipsters
to come forth.
And I hope that my $250,000
reward is still implemented
in that in that in that
tipsters payment.
>> but we need if we're if if
people get in trouble, who are
they going to call?
>> they're going to call the
police.
>> so why are we arguing over
this?
>> I know I will let another
one of my children get hurt.
I'll be calling the police.
>> thank you, MS..
Brown.
City.
>> all right.
Any other speakers who would
like to address the board for
the update to the police?
>> excuse me?
The reforms in the police
department.
All right, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
Public comment is now closed.
Supervisor walton thank you,
PRESIDENT Amendment and thank
you chief scott and thank all
of the public who came for the
hearing.
again, I do appreciate all of
the recommendations that have
been addressed.
I know we still have nine
remaining recommendations so I
would like to make a motion to
continue this hearing to our
OCTOBER 7th to 2025 board of
supervisors meet.
>> there is a motion is there a
second seconded seconded by
fielder.
>> and MADAM Clerk, can you
please call the roll on the
motion to continue?
>> item 38 to OCTOBER 7th 2025
supervisor engardio
and engardio is supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin.
Hi gentlemen I supervisor
melgar melgar I supervisor sadr
sadr I supervisor cheryl
sherrell I supervisor walton
walton I'm supervisor chin chin
I supervisor chin chin I
and supervisor dorsey dorsey I
there are 11 eyes the motion
passes and the hearing is
continued to OCTOBER seven
MADAM Clerk let's go to
committee reports item 39 was
considered by the government
audit and oversight committee
at a regular meeting on
thursday MAY 1st and was
forwarded as a committee
report.
Item 39 is a resolution to
declare the intention of the
board of supervisors to renew
and expand a property based
business improvement district
known as the ocean avenue
community benefit district
and to levy a multi-year
assessment on all parcels
in the district to approve the
district plan.
the engineer's report and the
proposed boundaries map for the
district to order and set a
time and place for a public
hearing of the board on JULY
8th, 2025 at 3 P.M. To approve
the form of the notice of the
public hearing and the
assessment ballot proceeding as
well as the assessment ballot
to direct environmental
findings and to direct the
clerk to provide notice of the
hearing and balloting as
required by law.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call.
>> without objection the
resolutions adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 40.
Item 40 was considered by the
land use and transportation
committee at a regular meeting
on monday MAY 5th and was
forwarded as a committee report
.
>> item 40 is an ordinance to
amend the public works code to
waive the tier three love our
neighborhoods major
encroachment permit fee for a
project to install the detroit
street steps archway in the
sunnyside neighborhood that
will create a gateway for the
detroit street steps project
and to amend the administrative
code to waive the board of
appeals surcharge for this
permit and to affirm the
section determination.
Same house, same call.
>> this ordinance is passed on
first reading MADAM Clerk let's
go to a roll call first member
up to introduce new businesses
supervisor and engardio submit
thank you supervisor fielder
submit thank you supervisor of
my put colleagues today
alongside supervisor sherman
walton I'm introducing a
landmark ordinance that has
long been overdue in san
francisco an ordinance to
ensure that san francisco takes
a more compassionate, fair
and strategic citywide approach
to addressing homelessness
and behavioral health needs for
residents.
>> homelessness is one of the
most intractable issues facing
our city.
For years san francisco has
tried a frank centered approach
to a problem that has continued
to worsen in our city
and across our state.
>> I represent the tenderloin
and where for many years
residents have seen the city's
humanitarian crisis firsthand
throughout the streets of our
neighborhood and every day we
see the real world consequences
of a system that is both
overburdened and broken
and neighborhoods that lack
services.
We see too many residents fall
through the cracks because
access to care depends on where
you live.
>> the solutions we've
implemented do not effectively
meet unhoused residents where
needed further exacerbating
issues and leading to
undignified living conditions
that are entirely preventable.
>> this ordinance aims to
guarantee equity in how
services are deployed, ensure
we meet residents in need where
they are and prioritize this
issue as one cohesive city.
>> right now neighborhoods like
the tenderloin soma the mission
in the bayview provide a
majority of the city's shelter
beds and behavioral services.
>> this overconcentration isn't
only straining our communities
schools, businesses and public
spaces it's created
inefficiencies in our service
system by placing the bulk of
services in just a few
neighborhoods making it harder
for those in need in other
parts of the city to access
shelter or care when they need
it most in several districts
there are literally zero
emergency shelters.
>> that is not a citywide
system.
It's a patchwork system that
fails residents in need
and overloads those already
doing the work.
>> accordingly, this ordinance
requires that by JUNE 30th 2026
every district approve at least
one new site a shelter
transitional housing or
behavioral health facility.
>> it establishes 1000 foot
buffer between new and existing
sites to prevent clustering
unless waived by the board for
a compelling public interest.
>> it also mandates twice a
year public hearings the
departments must report
transparently on progress
citing barriers and how many
people are actually being
served.
>> our current structure is
failing because it relies on a
handful of neighborhoods to
deliver care for an entire
city.
Over the last several months
I've talked to our hot teams.
I've talked to members of the
board.
i've talked members of the
public and I've heard countless
examples of residents who are
in need in their respective
districts.
But because there was no
shelter available, they were
put out into the streets
and some of them even
unfortunately passed away.
>> had services been available
near them, their loss of life
could have been entirely
preventable.
>> this failure in services
doesn't just hurt communities
like the tenderloin it hurts
individuals who can't access
care, don't receive a bed or
fall into cycles of crisis
because our services aren't
deployed where needed.
>> these aren't statistics on a
sheet.
Is someone's friend a brother
or sister or someone's child?
>> this ordinance creates a
functional citywide system of
change one where people are
housed faster services are
closer to where people actually
live and no one is left wasted
waiting in line or out in the
cold.
>> it builds on supervisor
walton's recently passed
resolution by turning policy
commitments into enforceable
law with measurable outcomes
and clear timelines.
>> it codifies a minimum
threshold of responsibility not
just for this mayor or this
board but for every
administration moving forward
because we won't always be here
but our responsibility for the
betterment of current
and future residents is written
in this piece of legislation.
>> it means residents in all
neighborhoods north southeast
and west can access shelter
and behavioral health support
without crossing the city,
without feeling like they're
leaving a piece of themselves
where they grew up.
>> it means residents
in neighborhoods like the
tenderloin and the bayview no
longer bear the burden alone.
It means better outcomes,
faster placements, shorter wait
lists and less burnout for
front line providers
and neighbors alike.
>> this legislation is backed
by those who know this system
best.
Tenderloin leaders, housing
advocates, service providers
and residents.
And before I close I want to
thank the tenderloin community
our residents, advocates
and service providers who have
been calling for this kind of
change for years.
This ordinance would not exist
without your persistence, your
organizing, your vision
and your heart.
I want to thank my coauthor
supervisor sherman alton walton
for his leadership in this
early on this earlier this year
with geographic equity
resolution and for being a
partner in this important work.
I'm grateful to our early
co-sponsors supervisor dorsey
sader fielder and melgar for
recognizing the urgency of
building a more equitable
and effective system.
I wanted to thank as well our
deputy city attorney anne
pierson for her thoughtful
and diligent work in drafting
this ordinance.
Thank my staff sam logan
and jessica gutierrez.
Garcia for their support on
this ordinance.
>> and I want to acknowledge
the continued commitment of
former tenderloin supervisors
jane kim and assembly member
matt haney, both of whom led
similar efforts on this
legislation and have endorsed
this plan as well.
>> colleagues, this legislation
was written as a commitment to
treating all residents with
dignity and compassion as a
promise to adhere to our
humanity and shared
responsibility in solving our
most pressing issues.
We are one city and I'm
encouraging all districts to
contribute to solutions that
uplift all of san francisco.
We must remember the collective
effort is essential for making
meaningful progress
and addressing homelessness
in a way that reflects our
city's values of equity service
and fairness.
This ordinance gives us the
structure to do that together.
>> respectfully ask for your
support and look forward to
partnering with all of you to
make this vision a reality.
>> thank you.
Supervisor mahmud.
Supervisor randleman.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I have a few
behavioral health hearings to
introduce.
The first is a hearing on the
findings and recommendations of
the residential care
and treatment workgroup.
The comptroller's office issued
this report on JANUARY 7th.
The final full day of the
administration.
>> mayor breed had at my
request convened the workgroup
following passage of
proposition one in MARCH of
last year to identify capacity
and placement gaps for people
with severe mental illness
in our residential treatment
portfolio and to develop
strategic recommendations to
guide the city's response to
the dire shortage of long term
beds for this population.
The work group's deliberations
helped lay the foundation for
the city's application
in DECEMBER of last year for
prop one funding to among other
things allow us to add
approximately 100 locked
subacute treatment beds to our
current portfolio of 140.
We anticipate hearing from the
state on the outcome of that
application imminently.
Whether or not we receive that
funding however, the issues
and strategies considered by
the workgroup deserve at the
very least a hearing before a
committee of this board to
inform our response to
california's decades old
failure to appropriately care
for indigent people with severe
mental illness.
I want to thank public safety
and neighborhood services chair
for finding time for us to have
this conversation on JUNE 26th
and I want to thank supervisor
fielder for her co-sponsorship
of this hearing on that same
date and at the same committee.
I'll also be holding a hearing
on san francisco's
implementation of senate bill
43 the legislation enacted
in OCTOBER 2023 and effect
and in effect since JANUARY of
last year updated the standard
for conservatorship of a person
who is gravely disabled by
among other things redefining
grave disability to include a
mental health disorder or
severe substance abuse disorder
that renders a person unable to
provide for their food,
clothing, shelter, necessary
medical care or personal
safety.
The legislation also made it
easier for courts to use
medical records to prove
eligibility in conservatorship
hearings.
>> the board of supervisors
supported sb 43 prior to
passage and now that's been
in effect for more than a year.
I think it's time for a check
in on how our city departments
and agencies are using this new
tool to provide care to people
who do not know they need it
and will not voluntarily accept
it.
And what challenges they're
finding in doing that?
My strong suspicion which I've
expressed frequently it's all
about the beds and without the
right kinds of beds.
The state legislature can amend
conservatorship laws ad nauseum
without significantly expanding
the number of people we're able
to move into conservatorship
care.
See my prior hearing
announcement.
Finally, I'm calling for a
hearing on fiscal year 20 2320
and the fiscal year 2023 2024
treatment on demand annual
report.
the 2008 treatment on demand
act also known as proposition t
mandates that publish this
report by FEBRUARY first of
each year.
It is supposed to provide an
assessment of the demand for
substance abuse treatment
services and provide a plan to
meet that demand.
>> this plan the law states
should be reflected in the city
budget.
As of today this report has
still not been released.
Although I strongly hope that
it will be while before our
hearing at p S.A. On JULY 24th.
Thanks again to chair dorsey
for finding time for this
hearing on the agenda for that
day and for his co-sponsorship
and the rest.
I submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar.
Thank you very much, MADAM
Clerk.
Colleagues today I am
introducing along with
supervisors and guardian
fielder chan cheryl and sardar
a resolution to show our
support and solidarity with
student journalists especially
those within our incredible
public schools.
>> as many of you MAY have read
in the chronicle, students at
the editorial board of the
lowell the excellent
publication of the journalism
program at lowell high school
felt intimidated by the
administration for publishing
an article describing verbal
harassment that some students
reported they faced from their
teachers.
The journalism teacher
and student newspaper advisor
at lowell schools were
subsequently reassigned.
This reporting was brave
and necessary.
>> these young journalists have
felt silence and intimidated by
the administration's actions,
including the retaliation
against their teacher.
This has had an intimidating
and chilling effect on these
young journalists and it is
unacceptable.
>> I am so incredibly proud of
these courageous student
journalists.
Their teacher the editorial
board of the lowell student
newspaper for taking a stand
in the face of intimidation
during these times when our
nation's constitution is being
undermined.
We must forcefully support the
right to free speech.
These student journalists
remind us that without a free
press we the people lose a
vital avenue by which we can
speak truth to power.
I want us to encourage students
in our public schools to use
their voice and for us as a
society to ensure that they are
provided the protection from
fear in retaliation.
>> colleagues also along with
at PRESIDENT Rafael mandel men
in the co-sponsorship of
supervisors dorsey, sheryl
and so
der I'm introducing a
resolution to celebrate
and recognize me as jewish
american history month.
We are so fortunate to have a
welcoming inclusive city that
has been the cherished home to
a jewish community that has
fled persecution from other
parts of the world including
including members of my own
family.
>> you are out of order.
Jews.
>> that is so unacceptable.
Supervisor.
>> unfortunately jewish
communities as we can have just
seen continue to face
persistent discrimination
and violence and the rise of
anti-semitic acts of hate
and rhetoric continues daily.
The ongoing violence in the
middle east has destabilized
the feelings of safety
and belonging for members of
our community.
Additionally, the trump
administration has used our
pain as a weapon to oppress
and suppress the civil rights
of others.
As a latina jew I also
recognize the complex
increasingly intersectionality
of repairing the world and how
representation can be impactful
justice.
Empathy and respect are all
essential components of peace.
This is what makes our city
and our country strong, young
and resilient.
Our diversity, our equity.
Our inclusion.
>> I want to thank the jewish
community relations council
especially jonathan mintz
and alejandro padrone along
with melanie matthew sun
and PRESIDENT Mandell mayor's
office for their work on this
resolution and for their work
in building bridges in our
community.
The rest I submit.
Thank you.
supervisor melgar and I
apologize for that
interruption.
Supervisor sartor thank you
MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues I am introducing
legislation today that will
update the underlying rules
and regulations of our city's
community challenge grant
program.
The community challenge grant
program or cg program was
created through a voter
approved ballot initiative
in 1990 and the ballot language
specifies that any changes to
the rules and regulations
require board approval.
So I am introducing legislation
to do just that.
This needed an overdue update
better aligns the program's
underlying regulations with
current procurement
and solicitation standards.
>> the establishing ordinance
as well as the overall goals of
this program.
>> this is an incredibly
valuable program.
This is one of the programs
that neighbors often turn to
when they're looking for
funding for community projects
like playground signs, gardens,
art installations, murals,
steps and other public realm
work.
Once this particular step is
complete we will be ready to
release a new request for
proposals to jumpstart public
beautification projects for our
neighborhoods something I know
that many throughout san
francisco particularly
neighborhood association
and community groups are
looking forward to.
so I will look forward to your
input and to working with the
office of the city
administrator to bring this
forward to committee for
discussion soon.
>> and the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sauder supervisor
cheryl submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton thank you so
much, MADAM Clerk.
And I want to thank my coauthor
on the geographic equity
legislation supervisor mack
mood and just reiterate the
fact that it's important that
we work together as a city to
address the issues and concerns
around our unhoused community.
I also want to thank our
co-sponsors.
I truly believe this will allow
all san francisco's the
opportunity of san francisco
residents the opportunity to
positively address
homelessness.
As we know this is a citywide
issue and that everyone wants
to see improvements.
The more beds, the more
services, the more permanent
and supportive housing that we
have across the city, the
better outcomes we will have
for everyone as we work hard to
address homelessness.
Today I want to formally
request that the budget
and legislative analyst's work
in coordination with the
comptroller's office conduct a
comprehensive audit of all
economic components of the
memorandum of understanding
between the police department
and the police officers
association.
this audit should include a
detailed analysis of pay
provisions, incentives
and financial impacts
associated with the agreement
as well as how these provisions
affect the overall city budget.
I'm also introducing a
resolution in support of
assembly bill 1414 authored by
assembly member rhodesia ransom
of stockton which protects
tenants fundamental right to
choose their own internet
service provider.
1414 is a critical step towards
digital equity in california to
ensure that no renter is locked
into an expensive, inadequate
or unnecessary internet plan
simply because of where they
live or who their landlord is.
In today's world access to
reliable affordable internet is
a basic necessity not a luxury
whether it's for work, school,
telehealth or staying connected
with loved ones.
Tenants deserve the freedom to
select the broadband service
that meets their needs
and budget.
This bill is especially
important for low income
families seniors and those
living in multi-unit buildings
where landlords are most likely
to strike exclusive deals with
their single isp.
Hb 1414 closes a critical
loophole and state law gives
renters the power to deduct the
cost of any forced isp
subscription from their rent
and aligns with existing
federal protections.
It's a commonsense policy that
strengthens consumer rights,
protects renters and promotes a
fair competitive internet
market in california.
The rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton.
Supervisor chan thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
>> and for first I would like
to denounce any hate speech not
only in this chamber but
against any of our community
members and just want to thank
supervisor melgar and board
PRESIDENT Mendelsohn for your
leadership not only honoring
but also representing a
jewish-american community.
I would like to add it to be a
co-sponsor honoring the
heritage hopefully not just
this month but really I think
all year round as we should
too.
And so with that I'm colleagues
I'm also introducing a
resolution today really
supporting and urging all of us
to support the fine food
workers strike.
San francisco and our airport
have a history of labor harmony
and peace provisions in our
contract support for airport
workers.
>> all workers but in this case
support for our workers to
exercise their autozone army
over their own labor and strong
public policies to support
worker protections.
>> but what we have seen now is
that flying food group has not
offer economic compensation to
adequately meet the expectation
of our workers.
Nor have they been negotiating
in good faith in which in turn
have prolonged it a labor
dispute with teamsters local
2785.
>> they've been on strike.
>> they are our truck drivers
and helpers at the flying
fruit group and the san
francisco international airport
.
>> they've been on strike since
APRIL.
And this is a resolution today
that I urge for your support
colleagues that we really
support the workers there
strikes but really also urge
all the parties to immediately
resume good faith bargaining so
that the workers can return to
work with dignity and economic
security.
And the rest I submit thank you
.
>> supervisor chan.
Supervisor chen thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
Colleague today I am
introducing a resolution to
support hb 1165 the california
housing justice act.
>> housing affordability is one
of the most pressing crisis of
our time impacting our local
workforce and it's the leading
driver of homelessness rent
burden and also housing
insecurity.
>> we know that meaningful
action is needed to ensure
every resident has a safe,
stable and affordable home.
>> and yet ongoing state
investments in housing
and homelessness account for
less than 0.5% of state annual
budget.
>> why?
California's leaders invested
in major one time resources for
housing and homelessness
in recent years.
We have bonds and one time
revenue sources.
This investments are not going.
this investments are not
ongoing and fall well short of
the scale needed.
>> this is not enough to
deliver the infrastructures or
assets or assisting the ability
to adjust housing
and affordability or end
homelessness without needed
stable funded assistance.
>> our local affordable housing
production and preservation
pipeline is staunch with local
partners unable to fully
complete their capital stack.
We know this this this will
only get worse as
administration
and congressional leadership
half sponsor it devastating
cuts for federal housing
funding ab 1160 five will
require the california
department of housing
and community development to
develop a finance plan to solve
homelessness and housing
affordability.
It established a california
housing justice fund in the
general fund and it requires
the legislature to invest in an
ongoing and u allocation in the
fund at the scale needed to
solve homelessness and housing
affordable and housing
unaffordability.
>> it is a hope and it's a bold
plan to create and protect
affordable housing, keep
renters stable house provide
rental assistance to prevent
and end homelessness and I'll
support services for people
with disability to stay
in their homes.
>> I want to thank my
colleagues supervisor walton
mamo and theater for their
early co-sponsorship.
and I also look forward to the
rest of my colleague to support
and urge california legislature
and governor to enact ab 1165.
>> I also have in memoriam.
Colleagues I would like to
adjourn today's meeting
in memoriam of carol lenny
maya.
>> kira was born on SEPTEMBER
17th JUNE 20th, 2005 and passed
it on MARCH 30th first of this
year.
>> she was a bright light
in the lives of many.
>> she will be deeply missed by
her brother brunson father john
myer and mom kathy mckee maya
kira ara was born and raised
in quaker emerson's.
>> she attended segar har kow
studio prep john jordan school
of equity for high school
throughout elementary school
kira a tutor kindergarten nurse
and immersed herself in musical
theater and dance.
She loved being on the varsity
volleyball team.
She was musically talented
playing the base violin,
ukulele and piano.
>> kira was active in the
community work with the woman
in action club and as a ucsd's
uv outreach worker.
During her time at aptos middle
school in her last year, kira
was running a pad
and housesitting business all
by herself.
>> she was active in community
organizing.
She was a fierce defender
and advocate for lgbtq issues
and had been awarded a
scholarship to attend the 2024
national lgbtq task force
creating challenges conference
conference in new orleans.
>> she was fighting for the end
of the genocide in gaza
and would often make stickers
and bring crafts for the kids
attending the marches
and pertussis.
MAY her memory be a blessing
and the rest I will submit.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
>> supervisor dorsey submitted
all rights and I think with
that we can go to public
comment yes public comment at
this time the board welcomes
your public comment please line
on your right hand side of the
chamber along the curtains you
MAY speak to the other general
matters that are not on today's
agenda but must be within the
subject matter jurisdiction.
All other agenda content will
have been reported out to the
world by an appropriate
committee where public comment
requirement occurred.
Can we have our first commenter
one moment please?
>> I am here concerning my son
robert couso who was murdered
AUGUST 14th 26th to this day as
cases unsolved.
As I mentioned earlier I come
here concerning I just don't
stand for my son.
>> there's all unsolved
homicides there unsolved
homicides.
So I'm just asking and this is
what they these are unsolved
homicides and I'm just asking
for the again, as I brought up
the ways to pay tipsters to
come forth this is I bring
these pictures with me all the
time to let the board of
supervisors and the police
commission know what we go
through as mothers and fathers
is just I'm I am a mother but
there's fathers that are going
through this also.
So I'm just praying that that
the way and when the proposal
to come up for the way the paid
tipsters to come forth that
everyone weigh in on this so
that myself and other families
can heal I bring these pictures
because this is what the
perpetrators that murdered my
son left me and I know you get
tired of looking at here come
MISS Brown again with those
pictures again.
But I will do this for the rest
of my life.
I will do this forever left
in my life.
I love my son and they took him
from me.
>> so please when it comes time
to find a way to pay tipsters
to come forth for our children
,please weigh on in.
I live in district five when my
son was murdered I still live
there.
>> I still have to walk and see
where his body laid.
>> please help.
Thank you for your comment MISS
Brown.
>> welcome to the next speaker
the afternoon PRESIDENT Mailman
and the board.
My name is paula wallace.
I am a business agent for
teamsters local 2785I was a ups
driver for 24 years.
On top of that I want to thank
supervisors sharon for this
important resolution and for
supervisors hassan fielder
and walton for co-sponsoring
our drivers add flying food a
private company with locations
across the country.
Contract with the airlines have
been on strike for 38 days.
These drivers bring the food to
stock the airplanes.
They are essential workers who
help the planes fly and for the
airport to run.
They are also low wage
immigrant workforce who work
under difficult and physical
conditions.
Our members who have sacrificed
their wages for 38 days to long
in pursuit of a fair health
care coverage in which every
person deserves health care is
under a threat in this country.
Congress will be taking a vote.
It will be taking a vote on
drastic medicaid cuts any day
now and san francisco must be
the leader in protecting the
health care and basic rights of
its workers.
Please consider co-sponsoring
the resolution to tell us I
phone the private vendors such
as flying foods that they must
act responsibly and settle a
fair contract.
Now if it is the duty of our
elected officials to protect
workers and not billion dollar
airline corporations and flying
foods that contract with them
thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker
when MR. Mccarthy and hear
about liberty and justice for
randy welch do you think it's
funny randy walsh doesn't just
address your comments to the
board as a whole?
>> okay.
There are members of the board
who think this is funny
and it's not.
This is from the health
commission yesterday.
Well, you the achievement of
five stores is a testament to
the quality of care provided
specifically laguna honda had a
very successful annual survey
this past fall where regulators
reviewed in detail resident
care and safety including
completing interviews with
residents.
That is not true.
My domestic partner randy walsh
doesn't even have standing at
laguna honda.
I don't have standing and this
domestic partner and I have
durable power of attorney
and goes on to say laguna honda
performed very well on key
metrics resident care
supporting resident care
behaviors, healing wounds,
preventing falls well that's
subjective.
You should see his back around
his head.
Well, they shaved off his hair
and he's got an inch and a half
story that's healing now this
is a second slip and fall.
Last time he had a fractured
ribbon and punctured lung
concerning overtime with the
police, one of the members of
the board of supervisors used
the term dishonest honest
services fraud is public
corruption.
Public corruption is a federal
crime.
>> there's always going to be a
lot of corruption and certainly
cisco as long as the feds stone
investigate or prosecute
concerning homeless people who
can't provide for their own
protection.
Nancy pelosi's husband was
almost murdered in his home
with a police officer standing
right in front of the store.
if you could be nancy pelosi's
husband with a police officer
standing in front of your door
and you can't provide for your
own protection, thank you for
your comments.
>> shouldn't you be conserved?
>> please welcome to the next
speaker.
>> good afternoon and thank you
to supervisor chan for your
leadership on important labor
issues and for introducing this
resolution around fang foods
and teamsters 2785.
And thank you to supervisors
chen fielder and walton for
co-sponsoring this morning.
Fang foods workers testified to
the airport commission that
they have not seen a raise
in over three years that they
need fair and affordable health
care and that they want to go
back to the job that they love
with a fair contract.
>> these drivers worked through
covid during which the airline
industry was bailed out on the
backs of back of taxpayers.
We ask that you see the people
who make the airport run as
essential now as they help the
airport and its vendors make
record profits.
>> we ask that each of you
co-sponsor this resolution
which strengthens the testimony
we heard from workers this
morning to ensure that flying
food settles a fair contract
with teamsters to 785 who have
been on strike without their
usual wages which is the most
extreme action a worker can
take for 38 days.
Thank you for your
consideration.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome kyle.
good afternoon, MADAM Clerk
PRESIDENT Mandolin and members
of the board kyle smylie on the
policy director for the san
francisco community land trust.
It's great to be back in the
chamber.
>> I'm here today to speak
in strong support of the
resolution backing assembly
bill 670 item 45 on today's
agenda ab 670 allows local
governments to count
investments in and preserving
housing toward their regional
housing needs allocation goals
preservation work isn't just
about saving old buildings it's
about keeping our communities
rooted.
It's about honoring the people
who've made san francisco what
it is the teachers who teach
our children, the restaurant
workers who nourish our
neighborhoods the artists who
give this city its soul.
Ab 670 recognizing recognizes
that preservation is a tool for
equity by funding
and empowering efforts
in communities that have been
historically left out of these
conversations we can help
ensure that working class
immigrant and bipoc residents
remain rooted in san francisco.
>> our city's character isn't
just architectural it's human.
Our residents are the beating
heart of this city.
Supporting 8670 helps uplift
that heart, protect it and pass
it on to the next generation.
I want to sincerely thank
supervisor fielder for her
leadership on this issue
and the co-sponsors supervisors
walton chan souder and chen.
I urge the board to vote yes on
this resolution and to continue
investing in community
ownership of land and housing.
>> before I wrap this is the
last board of supervisors
meeting for long time
legislative aide preston
kilgore.
>> I want to say thank you.
Okay.
You're one of the best to ever
do it.
Appreciate you so much.
>> thank you.
Thank you, kyle.
Right, right on.
Welcome.
>> hello.
You know, I had a whole thing
planned with talking about the
mayor and the budgets and how
he's like funding suvs
and staff for himself with his
own wealth and what's he doing
for us with his wealth?
>> nothing.
Blah blah blah.
But I mean, you just saw some
some more hate speech that
anti-semitic outbursts which
was totally offensive
and inexcusable and just how
these like incidents you know,
where various people, including
myself are now regularly being
harassed here this is not a
safe place anymore.
F y I I leave this place
emotionally drained and damaged
.
>> so let's just talk about
that.
In the transgender district,
the flags aren't up currently.
>> I don't know if the trans
flags are coming back.
I hope they are.
The castro is allowed to fly
flags.
>> I hope we're still a lot of
y transgender flags every day.
>> being a trans person in this
country is an assault on us.
Just this afternoon the supreme
court allowed trump's ban on
transgender troops.
>> do you know what happens
when the military like you're
not integrated into the
military?
It becomes easier for the
military to attack you because
you're not a comrade in their
training and and their family
affections.
You know, like the camaraderie
is not there with trans people
or women or black people like
people who have been excluded
from the military like it's not
just going to stop at trans
people either.
>> you should know that.
>> and just an example of why
it's very important to nip
things as soon as possible is
that offensive?
Man he was doing regular
outbursts and your security
didn't do anything and then it
escalated to what it did.
>> I know if I did that I
immediately would have been
shut down.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> all right.
If you are here for general
public comment, please line up
on the right hand side of the
chamber.
>> welcome.
This is general and for that
ident 42 and 44 yes.
>> excellent.
Are griffin lee here on behalf
of connected S.F. One wanted to
come out here and support I
think it's item 44 regarding
direct free housing ab 255
being presented by matt haney
we don't necessarily believe
in housing first but given it's
a drive line here in california
and across the country we do
believe in drug free housing.
>> we fully fully believe it's
essential to the recovery of
those on our streets and the
recovery of san francisco.
>> thank you.
Supervisor darcy and management
for showing up yesterday at the
rally so secondly on the
proposed legislation in the
introduction today while this
MAY sound a bit contradictory
I, I do want to express
opposition on behalf of
connected S.F. On the ordinance
that supervisor mumford is
proposing.
>> one is the reason is there's
no language thus far as long as
we can tell around costs
association associated with
shelters and behavioral health
centers being potentially put
in place.
>> secondly my supervisor my
move comes from the private
sector and I'm aware not every
analogy works between the
private and public sector
and comparing the two but the
underlying theme and thesis of
why we believe and oppose this
opposition to this ordinance is
because you do not spread a
problem where a problem does
not already exist.
>> I would at least urge
supervisor my mood to further
specify in in the context of
the ordinance especially
protecting areas around
schools, senior centers
and churches.
Thank you for your comments.
Thank you very much.
>> hello afternoon.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome.
>> hi.
Okay.
So a few things.
First of all, our airport
workers we absolutely do need
to find them.
We need to ensure that they're
making a wage.
When you address for compaction
there's inflation going on
in our economy that strain on
financial income for folks that
work in those employee
positions.
You need to make sure that
people are making the fair
wages that they need to
in order to provide for their
families.
When you don't do that then
that causes financial strain
and they're not able to run
their housing efficiently
and everything else like their
bills just like everybody here
has bills.
People out there have bills as
well.
The other thing is the truckers
you can adjust for compaction
as well as especially the
inflation there.
That's extremely important.
The other thing is I heard some
women speaking a little bit
earlier and I mentioned that
there has been representation
efficiently in representation
for the lgbtq community.
That's disheartening because
right around the corner is not
only juneteenth but also pride
month.
These are huge cultural events
that happen here in the city
that we uphold and is our
culture that has been here for
years for years.
It's what we stand for and what
we represent here.
Do not let that go to waste.
>> and then lastly let's make
sure that we're not losing out
on the things that we represent
that we stand tall on.
>> don't lose out on that.
I know there are some people
there's some new faces in here
.
Maybe they don't know how
things are done but we need to
make sure that we uphold the
culture of what we represent
here in san francisco.
If we can't uphold those values
here in san francisco, what
makes you think we can fight
in D.C.?
What makes you think we can
fight anywhere else if we can
uphold it here?
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
.
I apologize for my frustration
earlier.
It's unfortunately going to
continue.
I'll try to keep my rough
language to a minimum.
With regards to drug addiction
and all this, you've got the
perfect example of sobriety
here.
Matt dorsey so are we asking
matt dorsey the questions since
matt dorsey has fixed what we
what do we need to do to fix
the actual problem?
I just sent another email to
all the board of supervisors
while I was sitting here.
I've sent several emails to
danny sater due to him being my
direct supervisor.
I've spent no less than eight
hours in the past two and a
half weeks of my release
attempting to gain or obtain
mental health services from the
city of san francisco because
if I do not obtain those
services I will go back to
jail.
And if there's no attempt made
for me to receive those
services I don't get this leash
taken off of my ankle while I
get called a outside my window
when I identify as gay despite
being charged with a hate crime
for allegedly calling someone
else a.
Our systems are not rocket
science to fix.
I know that you guys are all
new to now.
Some a lot.
Some of you guys are new to
your positions here.
But the reason I brought up for
me attempting spending those
eight hours attempting services
is that I have not gotten a
response back from a single one
of those agencies receiving
millions of dollars in funding.
We don't need more funding.
We need people to actually care
and actually caring starts with
a response.
Danny souder.
I don't care about my across
the board as a whole.
I don't care about my criminal
history.
I care about not going back to
jail while people are smoking
fentanyl outside my window
and I pay for my apartment.
I'm not a freeloading drug
addict.
But I'm the person that needs
to get put on a leash after
getting strangled for 35
minutes.
and that hasn't hit the
airwaves.
Well, we thank you so much for
respecting jewish and we make
everything a race war versus
making it so I respect war.
>> I'll come by and I will get
your information.
Thank you.
Do you mind waiting?
Okay.
MR. PRESIDENT, are there any
other speakers who'd like to
address the board during
general public comment?
>> please come forward.
All right, MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
>> public comment is now
closed.
Um, MADAM Clerk let's go to ah
for adoption without committee
reference agenda items 43 to 40
five items 43 through 45 were
introduced for adoption without
reference to committee.
A unanimous vote is required
for adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Otherwise a member MAY re
acquire a reso to go to two on
first reading to go to
committee.
>> supervisor dorsey could we
pull item 44 a link 44
surprised melgar.
>> I just want it to be added
as a co-sponsor to 43 and 45
please.
>> hey MADAM Clerk that's
noted.
All right.
So on the balance of the items
MADAM Clerk.
>> clerk can you please call
the roll and items 43 and 45.
Supervisor engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandel min.
>> hi mandel min I supervisor
melgar I I melgar I supervisor
sadr sadr I supervisor cheryl
cheryl I supervisor walton
walton eyes supervisor chin
chin I supervisor chen chin I
and supervisor dorsey dorsey
either are lebanese without
objection the resolutions are
adopted.
And MADAM Clerk can you please
call item 44 item 44 a
resolution to support
california state assembly bill
number 255 introduced by
assembly member matt haney the
support of recovery residents
program to enable state
investment and establish a
certificate certification
process for such programs.
>> supervisor dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Mandell
and colleagues yesterday
PRESIDENT Mandolin and I joined
mayor larry assembly member
matt haney and dozens of
members of san francisco's
recovery community to express
our support for assemblymember
haney's ab 255.
This legislation continues the
assembly members work to
authorize state investment
in drug free and recovery
housing options and to create a
certification program for that
kind of housing.
As you MAY know, this
resolution is substantially
identical to one we passed
without opposition last year.
California is existing housing
first policy enacted in 2016
mandates that 100% of state
funded permanent supportive
housing include drug tolerant
lease provisions.
That approach unfortunately
ignored guidance from the obama
administration the previous
year that housing first should
include drug free and recovery
housing options for those who
want them.
Unfortunately, california's
approach effectively prohibited
drug free housing options with
the way that it crafted its
housing first core components.
Assembly member haney's
legislation will update that to
allow for up to 25% of funding
for permanent supportive
housing to be for recovery
housing options.
This responds to the need he
has heard and I have also heard
from many constituents we share
who are striving both to exit
homelessness and maintain their
sobriety and recovery and who
are asking us for options for
drug free and recovery oriented
housing.
I want to thank assembly member
haynie for his championship of
these issues and for his
thoughtful work on this
legislation.
Likewise, thanks to another
former colleague of ours are
now assembly member catherine
stefani for her leadership to
support recovery housing
and for drafting the original
resolution we supported last
year.
Thanks as well to mayor lurie
for his individual endorsement
of ab 255 and for being a
strong champion for san
francisco's recovery community.
Finally, thanks also to my
colleagues who voted to support
this last year and I hope I
will have your support on this
again.
>> thank you.
thank you.
Supervisor dorsey I think we
can take this item same house,
same call without objection the
resolutions adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, do we have any
imperative agenda items?
There are none to report.
MR. PRESIDENT, could you please
read the in memoriam?
>> yes.
Today's meeting will be
adjourned.
>> excuse me.
In memory of the following
beloved individual.
On behalf of supervisor chen
for the late MISS Kira lani
meier.
Right.
I believe colleagues at that
brings us to the end of our
agenda.
>> MADAM Clerk.
Is there any further business
before us today?
That concludes our business for
today.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
We are adjourned